<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The golden law and emperial principle, or, The universal monarch viz. the soveraignty of salus populi (not voluntas nor voluptas populi) over all powers and potentates whatsoever ... : besides many other usefuls, to rectify and so to satisfie the conscience scruples of all sorts about the high and disputable point of this time, as, who hath right to the government of our three countries ...</title>
            <author>Hunton, Samuel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 191 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86921</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3786A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43645</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">42475053</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 42475053</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151178</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86921)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151178)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2248:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The golden law and emperial principle, or, The universal monarch viz. the soveraignty of salus populi (not voluntas nor voluptas populi) over all powers and potentates whatsoever ... : besides many other usefuls, to rectify and so to satisfie the conscience scruples of all sorts about the high and disputable point of this time, as, who hath right to the government of our three countries ...</title>
                  <author>Hunton, Samuel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 104 [i.e. 96] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.M. for William Lee, and are to be sold at his shop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Numerous errors in paging.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Divine right of kings --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151178:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE GOLDEN LAW, AND EMPERIAL PRINCIPLE, OR THE Univerſal Monarch, <hi>ViZ.</hi> The Soveraignty of <hi>Salus populi</hi> (not <hi>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas</hi> nor <hi>voluptas populi</hi>) over all Powers and Potentates whatſoever; yea, over all things in this World, though never ſo ſacred, or precious, as over our Religion and Laws, Lives and Liberties, as here is cautioned; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that God himſelf, prefers man, and complies to him in all things, when in juſt competition; Beſides many other Uſefuls, to rectify and ſo to ſatisfie the conſcience ſcruples of all ſorts about the High and Diſputable Point of this Time; as, who hath right to the Government of our three Countries, <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. making good alſo this Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, that Individual Rights may not Rival it, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, but comply as doth God, rather then endanger the ſafety of <hi>Salus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <q>Better it is, that one <hi>Man</hi> die (much more loſe his <hi>Right,</hi> if any) then the whole <hi>Nation</hi> periſh, to <hi>in-right Him.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>COurteous Reader,</hi> Read, I heartily entreat thee, both the Epiſtle to the Reader and the Contents alſo, for they will I hope not only content thee, but give thee light alſo into what ſhall, as into the Book following.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. M.</hi> for <hi>William Lee,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in <hi>Pauls-Chain,</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:151178:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151178:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS HIGHNES, THE Lord Protector.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe Your <hi>Highneſs,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Hould I either of ignorance, or as fearing to preſume (as it may be call'd) not Dedicate this to You, yet the thing it ſelf ſo relates to Your <hi>Highneſs,</hi> as that it ſelf-ly doth it, do I what I can: I hope then it will not be notion'd <hi>Preſumption,</hi> if <hi>I</hi> bear it company, and come along with it in theſe Lines, reverently to dictate for it, as <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> for <hi>Moſes,</hi> alſo, as ſo poſtur'd, to wait
<pb facs="tcp:151178:3"/>
on your <hi>Highneſs,</hi> and withal, to crave pardon, if I make bold to ſubſcribe my ſelf</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your</hi> Highneſs <hi>moſt humble Servant,</hi> S. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:151178:3"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath been, and is at this inſtant, the great Controverſie of this <hi>Nation,</hi> who it is that hath right to the <hi>Government,</hi> &amp;c. and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive Arms are taken up in behalf of <hi>Ch. Stuart,</hi> under pretenſe of his right thereto, which enforceth defenſive Arms to oppoſe <hi>Him,</hi> as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no ſuch right, alſo to prevent factioning for <hi>Him,</hi> to the endangering our Countries to ruine. Our <hi>Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in this following Tract, is, to clear this <hi>Point</hi> ſo fully, as that the weakeſt capacity may (if not wilfully blind) plainly ſee it; Our <hi>Hopes</hi> are, that when its ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, they will then ſide with the right ſide, for <hi>Right</hi> ſake, ſo for their own, and their <hi>Countries</hi> peace and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſake, and to ſave it, and themſelves, and theirs from <hi>Ruine.</hi> Courteous <hi>Reader,</hi> Read through I pray thee, before thou judgeſt; the Roman and Pagan <hi>Laws</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn thee to do ſo, how then do the Chriſtian Laws of Juſtice and Charity? So that, if this or that diſtaſte thee, or reſolve thee not, thou yet ſhalt I hope be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in both, before thou haſt done, and ſo I have done, and reſt thine. And yet</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Courteous Reader,</hi> I muſt make bold, for a few words more, I heartily entreat thee, of thy humanity and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility to excuſe the common and trivial ſlips of Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphy and Pointing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo if ſome Capitals ſhould want their Italica diſtinctions and ornaments, the like for Method, all which though uſeful and pleaſing, yet
<pb facs="tcp:151178:4"/>
are immaterial to <hi>Matter,</hi> and but ceremonies to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, as Roſe-leaves, and Verge-ſalt are to a ſound and wholſome diſh of meat; yet would I have accomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated thee with thoſe alſo, but neceſſitated interruptions checkt me. In ſhort, let thy goodneſs excuſe our fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and accept well our fair intentions and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, though they want the beauty of taking language, which hides almoſt all other defects; and yet the truth is, I aymed aimed both at Reaſon and Rhethorick; but principally the firſt, as firſt in worth and chiefdom; for let all know, that its an eaſie buſineſs to write Hiſtories, or Relations, which is but to tell Tales finely, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of ſelf abilities, except trimneſs of rendring, but thoſe that define, bound, and circumſcribe aright, had need to have the ſpirit, the ſoul, and energie of Reaſon, for nothing is ſo deep, ſo high, ſo ſoaring, and ſearching, nor ſo approaching to a God, as is god-like Reaſon. As for Rhethorick, its a fine, a nice, a beautiful vanity. But to Reaſon (ſay all ſorts what they pleaſe) all Powers Mortal, or Immortal (but the Immortal God) muſt ſtoop, and do homage to; and yet this Romiſh Harlot Rhetorick, hath by her Paintings, and Dreſſings, and her Wiles and Impoſtures, for Impoſt ſake, as for ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhrines, ſoveraignty and ſalary, got the ſtart or bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of her, cauſe moſt men are bad and naught in points of intentions or judgements; and now <hi>adieu,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>S. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:151178:4"/>
            <head>The Contents of the Book.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> HIS Highneſs Right to the Government is made good at <hi>Sect. 43.</hi> to <hi>53.</hi> ſo at <hi>78.</hi> All Objections againſt Him are anſwered as they fall out.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> That neither <hi>Charls Stuart,</hi> or any of that Race, have now any Right thereto, is made apparent at <hi>Sect. 75.</hi> to <hi>78.</hi> So <hi>Sect. 16.</hi> to <hi>18,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> What unjuſt Uſurpation is, <hi>Sect. 101.</hi> which quits his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> beſides the References for his Rights afore.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> What Arbytrarie Government is, which alſo quits his Highneſs, ſo any Governour ſo governing, though Law with our cautions be deviated or declined.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5. Moſes</hi>-ſtory-ſtoryed, or ſet out: ſee at <hi>Sect. 79.</hi> which ſuits with his Highneſs caſe and condition at this time.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> The grand and puzzling queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> who ſhall be Judge in all Diſputes, Things, Caſes, Queſtions, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies; reſolved at <hi>Sect. 83.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> The power and place of the Univerſal and Higheſt Publike Judge, or Magiſtrate, <hi>Sect. 102.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> Many uſeful things concerning Law, and Lawyers, and other requiſites you ſhall find here and there.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> The Soveraignty of <hi>Salus Populi,</hi> or the publike Peace and Welfare is made good by <hi>Sect. 2,</hi> to <hi>Sect. 18.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10.</hi> An Anſwer to thoſe who except againſt our Armies, or Forces by Land and Sea, and Taxes thereon, ſee <hi>Sect. 72.</hi> and that they are ſlaves, and not Free-men.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:151178:5"/>
                  <hi>11.</hi> Some <hi>Uſefulls</hi> of <hi>Magna Charta, Sect. 106.</hi> to <hi>113.</hi> ſatisfied.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12.</hi> An humble Addreſment to his Highneſs, or any Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, in behalf of the People, for remedy of things amiſs, and to prevent clandeſtines, and ſo any trecherous plots to aſſaſinate, or the Inſurrections of the people; ſo all bold, impudent, uncivil, rude, and Booriſh clamours and excla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations to incenſe the People to an endangering the Peace and ſafety of the Nation, <hi>Sect. 124.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13.</hi> An anſwer to the exceptions againſt ſuch an Addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Sect. 125.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14.</hi> An Addreſment to all Forraign States, Kings, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or Governours whatſoever, in behalf of their People, &amp;c. <hi>Sect. 126.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15.</hi> An Apologie to all our worthy Commanders, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, Officers, and common Souldiers to ſatisfie them why we attribute all the brave atchievements, to his Highneſs name only, <hi>Sect. 127.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16.</hi> A Caution to Lawyers, <hi>Sect. 114.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17.</hi> A Paradoxical concluſion, <hi>128.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151178:5"/>
            <head>SALVS, HER SOVERAIGNTY, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E are conſtrained by the ignorance and pravity of the <hi>Multitude,</hi> to <hi>Tautoligize</hi> it in repetitions, even to a wearying of our <hi>ſelves</hi> and the <hi>world</hi> with words, and yet it will not do, and therefore we muſt yet do it; So we are forced to preſent our ſelves on the <hi>Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> once more in behalf of<note n="*" place="margin">The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and welfare.</note> 
               <hi>Salus</hi> her <hi>Soveraignty,</hi> ſo in behalf of <hi>Salus</hi> her<note n="*" place="margin">The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour.</note> 
               <hi>Soveraign,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Her <hi>Soveraignty</hi> we make good by the Arguments following. His by <hi>Sect.</hi> 43. to 53. ſo 78. to 83.</p>
            <p n="2">§ 2. We wil firſt begin with <hi>Scripture</hi> Arguments the better to infallible it, yet as fortified with right <hi>Reaſon</hi> alſo, in things of this nature, elſe were they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited, &amp;c. We will next purſue it with right <hi>Reaſon,</hi> which wil <hi>ſelf-ly</hi> infallible it, yet not to the<note n="*" place="margin">Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants and conceiteds</note> 
               <hi>ſelf-iſh;</hi> but together we dare inſcribe it with—<hi>Scriptum eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:151178:6"/>For <hi>Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">§ 3. <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith, the <hi>Sabbath</hi> was made for <hi>man,</hi> yea for <hi>Individuals,</hi> how then for the <hi>Univerſal.</hi> It was made for him chiefly in points of humanity, as in Acts and Offices of Mercy, Charity, Love, Juſtice, and juſt neceſſities; ſee <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. That thou and thine, both ſervants and beaſts may reſt, and remember that thou waſt a ſervant in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and how acceptable and welcome <hi>Reſt</hi> was, or would have been to thee, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Thus, in juſt competition, all things comply to <hi>Humane</hi> neceſſities, and God is then beſt ſerved, in the omiſſion of <hi>Sacrifice</hi> for <hi>Mercy;</hi> ſo you cannot glorifie, honour, ſerve, love, obey, and worſhip God better, then to decline him, and incline to, or prefer Mercy before Sacrifice, that is, wave the Sabbath in its religious rites, duties, and obſervations, if they claſh with <hi>Mercy,</hi> make God then on juſt occaſions and grounds, a God of mercy, and you magnifie him moſt, for his <hi>mercy</hi> is above all his <hi>works,</hi> and doth <hi>magnificent</hi> him, but yet take heed you incroach not on <hi>mercy</hi>'s good nature beyond our cautions, which if you do, Juſtice will be meet with you, for ſhee is bound not to ſee <hi>Mercy</hi> abuſed.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Again, its better that one <hi>man</hi> die, then all the <hi>peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> periſh; and now all the <hi>people</hi> muſt periſh, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right one unrighteous <hi>man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. The <hi>Man</hi> then to die, was a righteous <hi>Man,</hi> the <hi>People</hi> he was to die for, were moſt unrighteous, &amp; yet he muſt <hi>die,</hi> that they may <hi>live.</hi> Now all the righteous people muſt <hi>die,</hi> for one unrighteous <hi>man,</hi> that he may live, to live on them, and Lord it over them.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The <hi>Man</hi> then to die, was a <hi>God</hi> alſo, the <hi>People</hi> he was to die for, were<note n="*" place="margin">By do genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</note> 
               <hi>Divels,</hi> and yet he muſt die, but now, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:151178:6"/>9. Thus much for <hi>Scripture</hi> Arguments in behalf of <hi>Salus</hi> Soveraignty, as juſtly neceſſitated: We come next to right <hi>Reaſon,</hi> which agrees with <hi>Scriptures,</hi> ſo its the ſame in Nature, though not in Name.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Right Reaſon ſaith then, That <hi>Phyſick</hi> and <hi>Food</hi> are ſervants to their ends, <hi>life</hi> and <hi>health:</hi> So <hi>Kings, Princes,</hi> and <hi>Powers,</hi> are the like to the Peoples ſafety and welfare; there being no other end and uſe of them as ſuch, but ſuch, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Moreover, we ſee that all ſorts do, and muſt one ways or other as they are able, venture their ſingle In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividual perſons, lives, eſtates, and rights for the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, or may be juſtly enforc'd, elſe the Publike might periſh, and ſo the Individuals thereof.</p>
            <p n="12">12. <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> ſo Law, Priviledges, and Rights, are pleadable twixt Individuals, and juſtice is their due accordingly; but not by any one againſt the higheſt publike Governour, in oppoſition to publike neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or as they claſh therewith, of which, how, and on what terms he is Judge, judge ye by <hi>Sect.</hi> 83. &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Here no Law for, or if a Law againſt, is of no value, the <hi>Principality</hi> of our <hi>Principle</hi> will not allow thereof, as you ſhall find ere we have done, and you do find afore what God hath, doth, and will do in the like caſe, in what relates to him. In ſhort, we cannot allow <hi>Law,</hi> which is but a bare name, a very nullity in this caſe, a dead thing, enlivened onely by letters and words, but moſt by <hi>opinion,</hi> to <hi>Lord</hi> it over its<note place="margin">the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick.</note> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> whoſe ſervant it is, and by and for whom it was made, and may (if it carry it ſelf amiſs) be chaſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed: Sure it was not rais'd to raze him, &amp;c. The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Law-makers, were Law-breakers, as the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like was neceſſitated.</p>
            <p n="15">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:151178:7"/>15. I conceive by all the aforeſaids, that <hi>Salus</hi> Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty ſtands clear, and is apparent, and ſo who are true, and who are Traytors thereto; ſo that now we may venture to inſcribe it with <hi>Scriptum eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We next reaſon and infer from the aforeſaids as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, That</p>
            <p n="16">16. Seing <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Laws,</hi> ſo <hi>Religion, Reaſon,</hi> the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> likewiſe <hi>Individual</hi> rights, yea the very lives, honours, and eſtates of good, honeſt, juſt and innocent men, have, do, and muſt on juſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, loſe and decline all ſelf-rights, and comply to neceſſitated <hi>Salus.</hi> What then can nocent <hi>Charls Stuart,</hi> or his ſiders with, ſay for themſelves, who for forfeited deputative Rights, forfeit their faith, love and loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty to their Lord, the <hi>Publike</hi> welfare, by exigenting it to intolerable ſufferings and dangers, yea to ruine by factioning their Country into Diviſions and Parties one againſt another in an hoſtile way? Do they not by this render themſelves <hi>Traytors,</hi> as contrary to truſt, duty, and engagement, to <hi>trecherize</hi> it? Are they not <hi>Murtherers</hi> and <hi>Thievs</hi> of all ſlain, and loſt, and taken from on both ſides, as inforcers thereto? I appeal.</p>
            <p>Again,</p>
            <p n="17">17. His Right to the <hi>Crown</hi> is not Natural, or ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Hereditary, but politick, and deputative, and ſo is, as are other <hi>Laws,</hi> alterable, (though they had not forfeit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it) as is conducing to the welfare and ſafety of <hi>Salus,</hi> how then as forfeited alſo? On which grounds they did make it <hi>Null</hi> by an <hi>Act,</hi> and by another <hi>Act</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned him, as ſiding with his Father &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="18">18. And as there is a <hi>Law</hi> that made it <hi>Treaſon,</hi> and ſo to forfeit ſelf-rights of life, and livelyhood, as of lands and eſtate, &amp;c. for attempting againſt the <hi>King,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:151178:7"/>
as the <hi>Publike</hi> welfare was concerned in him, and the King did, and might by Law and Reaſon exact the ſame, as ſo relating to the publike good of peace and ſafety; by the ſame Law of Reaſon, or <hi>lex talionis,</hi> as much is due upon the <hi>King,</hi> or any of his, yea more, as more engaged by truſt, oath, honours, and tribute or revenues, of and from the <hi>people</hi> for that end and purpoſe; and the King himſelf by his <hi>opinion,</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action of the ſame, ſaith as much, and ſo condemns himſelf and his for Delinquents, as ſo acting, and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies his executioners for their acting thereafter on ſuch. If it be ſaid, that the King traytor'd ſuch, or as it related to himſelf only, and not as to the Publike. I anſwer, It may be ſo, but it rendred him weak, or wicked and unjuſt, or both if ſo; for it was, and is in Nature and Reaſon, and intention of Laws, ſo the Law-makers, as we ſay afore, as it publikely related, &amp;c. for what's <hi>Unus</hi> to the <hi>Univerſe,</hi> or to our higheſt principle, alſo of one ſo engaged as afore, by truſt, oath, and tribute, and ſo his end of being what he was, and having what he had?</p>
            <p>But to abſolute this point, I will make bold to inſert a few lines juſt as they are in my <hi>Army Armed,</hi> which ſure with what's ſaid, will ſatisfie or ſilence each one.</p>
            <p>We will ſuppoſe then as high as we can, as that <hi>Charls Stuart</hi> is innocent, and abſolutely wronged of his right, What then? yea further, ſuppoſe they were his ſelf-rights, as they are not; and not forfeited, as they are; what then? Where doth any one find it in the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that to inright one, they may hazard the ruine of millions; if the wronged could right themſelves the right way, as on the wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers only, I diſpute not againſt it; but to wrong infinite
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151178:8"/>
               <hi>innocents</hi> to right one nocent, or admit <hi>innocent,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which yet they may fail, is unſpeakable madneſs, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and injuſtice: by this why may not <hi>Clients</hi> clearly injured by their <hi>Lawyer,</hi> or their <hi>Adverſary, hoſtile</hi> it, and gather an Army of men, <hi>Eſau</hi>-like, and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force his <hi>Adverſary</hi> to do as much for his defence; ſo theſe two <hi>Murtherers</hi> muſt meet with their <hi>multitudes,</hi> and the <hi>innocent fools</hi> on both ſides muſt murther each other, under the notion of ſiding with for rights, and yet may this be much better done for known ſelf-rights, then for known forfeited <hi>deputatives,</hi> not to the ruine of a multitude only, but of a <hi>Nation,</hi> to whom they were bound by <hi>Oath, Honour, Truſt,</hi> and <hi>Tribute,</hi> and ſo owe duty and ſervice anſwerable.</p>
            <p>How alſo can Forraign Religious <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>States</hi> then in Honour and Honeſty anſwer it, to <hi>Murther</hi> and <hi>Thieve</hi> it, in pretending to help ſuch to their <hi>Rights;</hi> but the truth is, they help them only to be helpt in the like caſes; ſo we are like to have a mad world of it, when <hi>Religious Princes</hi> and <hi>States,</hi> as call'd, ſhall help to ſupport one another in <hi>Tyrannies, Thefts,</hi> and <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> under the <hi>Notion</hi> of <hi>Rights;</hi> but wo to thoſe that call <hi>good evil,</hi> and <hi>evil good;</hi> I marvel exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that ſuch <hi>juſt, religious,</hi> and <hi>honourable Princes</hi> and <hi>States,</hi> do not ſend over their Armies now and then, to help each <hi>innocent individual</hi> wrong'd of his ſelf-rights by his <hi>Adverſary,</hi> or his <hi>Lawyer:</hi> for its a much fairer, goodlier, and juſter ground and pretenſe then the other, though both be naught, as teaching both ſides <hi>naughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> as to invade each others rights, under pretenſe of <hi>righteouſneſs. Thus much for our</hi> Army Armed.</p>
            <p n="19">19. Shew they then not great weakneſs or wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, not to know, or not to acknowledge, things of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151178:8"/>
ſo eaſie a comprehenſion, made good as afore, by <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, Religion,</hi> and <hi>Reaſons,</hi> or to perpetrate ſuch trecheries and perfideous actions, contrary to all.</p>
            <p n="20">20. Shew they not both great <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> and <hi>Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> to expoſe their own Honours, Lives, and Eſtates, who many of them did and might have lived happily and Prince-like, or in a ſweet, comfortable, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent condition, but have now forfeited and loſt all the aforeſaids, upon ignoble, baſe, and trecherous ends, courſes, and deſigns, and ſo undone alſo their Wives and Children, and brought themſelves to end their days diſhonourably, miſerably and untimely: Is't nothing to expoſe all as afore, ſo their kindred and friends, and their native Country to the Sword, Fire, and Famine, beſides many other miſeries and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, as now in its prime of plenty, beauty, and bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very to devaſtation and ruine; as if <hi>Winter</hi> had anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipated it in time to ſeize on, and ſurprize the <hi>Summers</hi> Riches and Treaſure, and all her goodly ornaments and endowments, and ſo to render our Fields, Meads, and Downs, <hi>Golgotha</hi>'s and <hi>Akeldama</hi>'s.</p>
            <p n="21">21. Well, but all we have ſaid, or can ſay, will not do, for they love <hi>Charls Stuart,</hi> and hate the Lord <hi>Protector;</hi> the <hi>Firſt</hi> alſo hath <hi>Right</hi> on his ſide, the <hi>Laſt</hi> is very <hi>Unrighteous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">21. Goodly <hi>Arguments</hi> for love and hate, ſo for judging about right or wrong; however by this they are orthodox and authentick, in judgement there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they may love and hate any one, alſo act any thing as relates to either, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="22">22. But are not theſe <hi>trecherous</hi> colours and preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes? for do they not rather trecherouſly love and hate themſelves, as their own ends, luſts, and deſires, which in concluſion will ruine them? &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="23">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:151178:9"/>23. What are their allowable grounds for loving <hi>Charls Stuart</hi> at all, or at ſuch a rate and degree, as to degrade themſelves, and theirs, and their native <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> as afore: Will they ruine the <hi>Univerſe</hi> for <hi>Unus?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="24">24. As for his <hi>Right,</hi> it hath in part been anſwered at § 16. and ſee in full § 75. But for the <hi>wrongs</hi> done by his <hi>Father</hi> and Himſelf to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> they are paſt over in ſilence. Is't not an argument of impudence, or inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, or both?</p>
            <p n="25">25. They love not the <hi>Lord Protector,</hi> alſo he hath no right on his ſide, as they ſay; but we ſay, for his <hi>Right</hi> to the Government, ſee § 43, to 53.</p>
            <p n="26">26. And truly we find by their dealings, that they love <hi>Him</hi> not, yea we find that they hate him, &amp;c. But why not <hi>love?</hi> or why at all, or thus <hi>Hate?</hi> I conceive they are to ſeek of Reaſons or cauſes for either, but admit in admittals, as that cauſe were for both, and to their degree alſo, yet where learn they to revenge at all, how then to ſuch a height, likewiſe, to the hazard of their <hi>Countries</hi> ruine, by involving it into Factions and Parties, for that end; for is not his Highneſs at this time the very hinge on which the ſafety and welfare of this State hangs, reſts, and depends?</p>
            <p>But for all their objections and exceptions hitherto againſt him, they are I conceive, ſufficiently anſwered in our <hi>Army Armed,</hi> and <hi>Protector protected;</hi> ſo that reſervedneſs were better, and more becoming, alſo more fair and juſt, till they find the ſaid <hi>Anſwers</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, as inſufficient or unjuſt; as we have cautioned and qualified them.</p>
            <p n="27">27. Many good things hath he done, why are they paſt over ſo, Equity requires <hi>Retaliation,</hi> &amp;c. for which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151178:9"/>
of his <hi>Good</hi> Deeds then would you <hi>ſtone</hi> him; or if for any <hi>Evil,</hi> make it appear, or that it amounts to a <hi>ſtoning?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Oh you his immediate Aſſaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nators, you Madmen, you Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers, you Traytors to your Country, by indangering its ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine: Are you hired? ſo was <hi>Judas</hi> to murther himſelf as well as his Maſter. You fools, how think you to ſcape? The Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites have befool you, as they did <hi>Raviliac,</hi> to be preſently conveigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away by an Angel; but the Divel prevented the Angel, and Tyburn the Traytor.</note> or if it did, its for the <hi>Innocent</hi> to caſt the firſt Stone, and not the <hi>Guilty,</hi> ſo none ſhall be caſt: But were he guilty, and that to your degree, yet who au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſed you to caſt <hi>ſtones,</hi> &amp;c. which we ſhall make appear you may not do at all; How then as <hi>Salus</hi> ſafety is concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Him:</hi> For,</p>
            <p n="28">28. <hi>Know Friends,</hi> that had ſuch or ſuch an one murthered my <hi>Mother,</hi> and now opportunity of war favours me ſo, as that he being plac'd juſt oppoſite to me, I could kill him, but my Father is accidentally placed juſt afore, alſo cloſe to him, ſo that I cannot ſhoot, or kill one, but I muſt kill both; what fine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe trow will bear me out to attempt it, and ſo turn paracide to my Father, under colour of love, duty, and juſtice to my Mother, and of hate and revenge, to, and on her ruiner; ſurely, as ſo poſtured, I will not only ſpare, but protect what I can ſuch a naughty man. How then ought I to protect what I can, mine, and my Parents, and my Countries Protector, that hath oft ventured his life, and all his fortunes, to redeem and recover my well neer loſt <hi>Mother</hi>
               <note place="margin">Our Country ſo each one, and theirs.</note>, and doth ſtill ſave and protect her; why then at all offend him, &amp;c. much more ſeeing you cannot wrong him, but our Mother muſt ſuffer alſo.</p>
            <p n="29">29. On what grounds now take up Arms for <hi>Charls
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151178:10"/>
Stuart;</hi> as for his Right, ſo your love to him: We have already, and will further anſwer you in due place; So for your groundleſs hate to his Highneſs, or though grounded, &amp;c. So that now your Arms taking up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Notion of and for <hi>Charls Stuart,</hi> muſt needs be for your own by and baſe ends, as to ſide with him, hoping to inſinuate into him, and deceive him with ſuch and ſuch pretenſes, and ſo gain him to ſide with you, for your own ends ſake; though he alſo have his own ends alſo, as well as your ſelves; yet both of you, <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi>-like, agree in your <hi>Levities,</hi> your wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, &amp;c. againſt your ſelves and yours, and ſo your Country, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="30">30. Your ends muſt be then to be righted of your wrongs, as you will call them, ſo to help you to your Fields and Vinyards again which you have loſt by your former trecheries, alſo hoping of an addition and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enlargement of them; likewiſe of advancement to places of profit, power, honour, and command, &amp;c. to theſe, and not to <hi>Charls Stuart</hi> are ye Stewards.</p>
            <p n="31">31. But is not this to build Caſtles in the Ayr, as to hazard the certainties you have, and ſo go on in your Trecherizings, in hope of revenge and advancement, which are ſo remote in point of likelyhood as afore: Is not your advancements more like to be <hi>Hamon</hi> like, then that of <hi>Mordecat?</hi> Have not divers of you been already advanced and mounted to <hi>Hamons</hi> height, to your downfals? Will not Love and Loyalty to your Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Country, its Peace and Safety, ſo the experience of others ſufferings by ſuch attempts, and the infinite hazards you ſelf-ly run, alſo involve your Country into, nor the loſs of what you have and ſweetly enjoy, &amp;c. Will none of theſe I ſay warn you
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151178:10"/>
againſt your ſelves, who are only your own ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="32">32. How can you digeſt it? How anſwer it; thus to Traytorize, Murther, and Thieve it, to bring your ends about, under pretenſe for <hi>Charls' Stuart?</hi> and admit this alſo, how yet I ſay can you in points of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, reaſon, humanity, and juſtice, anſwer it? Care you not what you do, to undo all, and your ſelves alſo? There is not one Argument of wiſdom, ſenſe, reaſon; juſtice, or humanity on your ſide, in your way of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, pretend what you will, find one if you can; and if not, what are you in the mean while, that are in this neither wiſe, rational, true, nor honeſt, but the quite contrary to all; contrary then your ſelves in the aforeſaids; and ſo you ſhall know what you are, by what you ſhould be.</p>
            <p n="33">33. Should your <hi>Charls</hi> conquer, as its very unlike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, alſo infinitely dangerous, miſchievous, and hazar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous to an univerſal ruine, &amp;c. yet he conquers not: for whats that conqueſt to you, that conquers you, and yours, and your Country alſo, &amp; makes you all abſolute ſlaves to the conqueror ſo call'd, and the conqueror a ſlave alſo to his competitors: can you promiſe to your ſelves the priviledges you now enjoy from your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror, who is more remote in nature and grace<note place="margin">Good qualitiies and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo he is a ſtranger &amp;c.</note>, ſo alſo in power to help himſelf and you; for the <hi>Kingers</hi> of your King will be his and your King, &amp;c. and ſhew him only to hide their own King-hoods, ſo alſo their Tyrannies to, and abuſes of the people, which his name and preſence of King muſt cover, and theſe alſo will befool you with promiſes and pretenſes, to gain you to ſecond the King, that ſo ye may ſecond, and ſo firſt them, in points of Conqueſt, and ſo of Linghood,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151178:11"/>
and then you ſhall have plenty of <hi>Chymera</hi>'s, and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> in the Ayr, and Aery <hi>Utopia</hi>'s for your pains: thus <hi>Joab</hi>-like, with their ſmiles, they ſmite you under the fifth rib; you ſhall have Butter and Milk alſo in Lordly diſhes, &amp;c. but not one word of the <hi>Nail</hi>
               <note place="margin">Yours &amp; your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries.</note> that muſt pierce your <hi>Temples,</hi> and faſten you to the ground paſt riſing, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Know you the end and iſſues of war, when once begun, and on foot? Doth it not uſually immortalize it in <hi>Mortalities,</hi> and make ſport of caſting Firebrands in good earneſt, as if in jeſt, like <hi>Joab</hi> and <hi>Abners</hi> gallants, that roſe up to play, but never lay down again till tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled down? Is not lovely, youthful, and natural green, a more ſeemly, comfortable, and acceptable colour for your grain and graſs, ſo for your Orchards, Gardens, Edens, and Paradiſes, then is the bloody, the gory, the ſavage, or ſanguine hew? Would you have Foot and Horſe, Troops and Companies, devour up, demoliſh, or trample down your goodly Corn-fields, ſo your Granaries and Graſs, and render all as diſmal as a deſerted Deſert? Muſt the Summer, and you be thus ſurpriſed, prize you all at no better rate then ſo? Would you return to <hi>Egypt</hi> again, the houſe of Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, and ſo have the <hi>Star-chamber</hi> ſtare over you as afore, and the High Commiſſion commit you <hi>ad placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum?</hi> Would you that Doctors Commons ſhould once more turn you to graze on the <hi>Commons?</hi> Would you that <hi>Pole-money,</hi> and <hi>Monopolies,</hi> alſo <hi>Ship-money,</hi> ſhould oppreſs you again? Think you that <hi>Taxes, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome,</hi> and <hi>Exciſe</hi> ſhall ceaſe? No, no, weaklings they are, as is the <hi>Militia,</hi> Flowers of the Crown; if theſe wither, whither will the Crown go? for ſo the Militia will be maſtered, for want of its Miſtreſs<note place="margin">Pecunia.</note>, &amp;c. But
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151178:11"/>
this muſt not be; as for us, we are forc'd to have the ſaid Seſments for defence ſake, they for offence ſake, though none offend them: Would you that <hi>Prelacy</hi> and <hi>Prieſthood</hi> ſhould perk up again, and under pretenſe of <hi>Religion,</hi> Gods honour, worſhip, and ſervice, and non-conformiſt &amp;c. be-heretick, and ſect you, and then diſſect you by perſecutions, puniſhments, and baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, alſo hamper your licentiate liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as they will call them, as ſo many extravagancies from the Orthodox Faith, and their implicite foole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; then when too late, your prudence will ſee your improvidence, to loſe ſuch a favour, through your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibleneſs, ingratitude, and licenciateneſs, &amp;c. then may you (like the <hi>Brazen-head</hi>) cry out, that <hi>time was,</hi> but <hi>is not,</hi> for now <hi>its past.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="35">35. Nor do I reaſon cunningly, on purpoſe to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh his <hi>Highneſs</hi> in the <hi>Government,</hi> otherwiſe then I conceive is right, alſo conduceth to the peace, welfare, and ſafety of our Nation, &amp;c. beyond any change that can be accidentally or forcibly made; but as for what may be carefully, wiſely, and peaceably contrived for his <hi>Highneſs</hi> Honour, and his <hi>Poſterities</hi> ſafety, and our <hi>Nations,</hi> &amp;c. ſurely will in prudence and providence be complyed to; for, the ſafety of the Nations is his, ſo each ones ſafety, &amp;c. ſo its hazards, dangers, exigents, or ruine, are his, ſo his poſterities, ſo each ones alſo; for they are ſo interwoven, that the web will be quite loſt, if either be loſt, &amp;c. <hi>Perſonal</hi> greatneſs may be good and neceſſary for the honour of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the <hi>Preſenter</hi> of ſuch a People is ocularly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous, as well as in Fame and Name; for that ſuch appearances begets it: as they did in <hi>Salomon,</hi> who made uſe of both, to beget, amplifie, and continue
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151178:12"/>
his greatneſs: and as the Mayor of <hi>London</hi> muſt not only in name <hi>Lord</hi> it, alſo in power and extent of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and Government, exceed <hi>Barnets,</hi> or <hi>St Albons</hi> Governours, but alſo in ocular and ſpecious <hi>preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> elſe his Sun of glory may decline, and retro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade it, as on the Dyal of <hi>Ahaz.</hi> With all humility I do therefore preſume, as love, duty, and loyalty binde me for his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> ſo our <hi>Countries</hi> welfare and ſafety, ſo each <hi>Individuals,</hi> that in ſeaſon, before death natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, or caſual prevent, thoughts may be how to leave this our Country, now under his <hi>Highneſs</hi> charge, ſo his <hi>Poſterities,</hi> ſafe and ſecure, in its after way, manner, and kinde of Government, leſt <hi>Greatneſs</hi> alone without <hi>Safety</hi> bring us all to little or nothing; it will much conduce to his <hi>Highneſs</hi> honour, ſo to his ſafety, whilſt living, for when the adverſary ſees his hopes daſht by a future certain way of ſafe Government, he will find it bootleſs to attempt on the preſent <hi>Governour,</hi> or fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and for my part, let his <hi>Highneſs Poſterity</hi> have the name and honour of the <hi>Preſentment</hi> thereof; yet in ſuch a ſecure way, as may ſecure themſelves and us all; which ſure for their ſafety, ſo our Countries, his <hi>Highneſs</hi> will comply to, and caſt for, as for his own life time, I do think that all or moſt do conceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be as well and ſafe under him, as under any other Governour whatſoever, from experience of his care and wiſdom hitherto. But <hi>Sir,</hi> you are <hi>Mortal,</hi> and withal momentary, therefore honour your <hi>Name,</hi> and your <hi>Poſterity,</hi> whilſt here, and when gone, by ſo providing for them, that ſo al ſorts may account you their <hi>Countries Saviour,</hi> next their Saviour: Sure, I am a Member of our <hi>Nation,</hi> and ſo concern'd in duty and with all humility, to exhibit my conceptions, by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151178:12"/>
way of hints and memorandums; for its and your good Sir, as the <hi>Syrians</hi> ſervant ſaid, to his Lord and Maſter familiarly; Father, what if the Prophet had ſaid for your good ſo and ſo; how then when he only adviſeth you to waſh and be clean, return home, ſafe, ſound, and ſecure, &amp;c. and his ſervants advice he took well, and obeyed it, and ſo was ſaved, &amp;c. elſe &amp;c. Did not the Lord <hi>Joab</hi> alſo hear a poor <hi>woman</hi> from the Wall, &amp;c. by which King <hi>David</hi>'s City was ſaved, ſo the Citizens, and the Lord <hi>Joab</hi> and his <hi>Army</hi> alſo? All which elſe in oppoſition might have been loſt, and deſtroyed one another. And <hi>Salomon</hi> hints alſo of a poor man that ſaved another City, but &amp;c. Its the higheſt of honours to leave all ſafe; and they and theirs are worthy of honour and dignities that do it; but ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and greatneſs without ſafety, is to ſtand on the precipe of a <hi>Precipice,</hi> as pinacled on the higheſt point of the <hi>Temple,</hi> ready for precipitation; which thou O <hi>God</hi> in heaven, and you <hi>gods</hi> on earth, I humbly pray you forbid, by timely providing for and againſt, all for, and againſt; which till it be, this whole <hi>Nation</hi> ſtands ſo placed as afore, though not minded, if your <hi>Highneſs</hi> ſhould miſcarry which God forbid; for I ſee ſuch clandeſtines and ambuſhments attend continually for your ſurpriſal, that I faint on thoughts thereof, both for you, and yours, our ſelves, and the whole <hi>Nation,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="36">36. But yet fully to clear it, that I partialize not in my plea in behalf of his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> let's ſuppoſe that <hi>Perkin Warbeck,</hi> or the Traytor <hi>Raviliac,</hi> or the Rayler <hi>Rabſhekah,</hi> or the <hi>Excepters</hi> own ſelf, had inforcedly, and ſo uſurpingly gained the Government, and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed much amiſs alſo, but not deſtructively, I yet would, yea I ought to ſupport them, though not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151178:13"/>
for their own ſakes, yet on the terms and cautions at Sect. 28. <hi>viz.</hi> as my Father, my Mother, my Countries ſafety is concerned in them, except I could evidently find a way to diſplace them without endangering our Country to murthers, ſlaughters, fire, famine, and all ſorts of devaſtations to ruine, alſo ſafely and certainly, without the aforeſaid miſeries, ſupply their places with better men, &amp;c. elſe as good abide as we are, as run ſuch hazardous adventures, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="37">37. Why then attempt againſt the <hi>Lord Protector?</hi> whom we have or will prove no <hi>Uſurper,</hi> but to have a true and juſt Right to the Government, as alſo governs well, though not to each ones fancy or minde, nor may, nor can, &amp;c. For God himſelf in <hi>Samuel</hi> could not do it; for no remedy, but they would diſcharge him, though they could no ways charge him, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="38">38. Would his Highneſs reſigne, and will us to fit our ſelves with Governours and Government to our minds, the whole Land would be in a confuſion; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions (like <hi>Hydra</hi>'s heads) would multiply, and ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide us, we ſhould never agree, cauſe each one would have his friend, or one of his Church or Faction to rule, that ſo that party or faction might rule in and by him: Are we not in a happineſs then that the place is poſſeſſed, by which means we are kept from ruining our ſelves, to place one there; who when there, though it were God himſelf (as afore) he cannot pleaſe men of contrary minds, humors, and ends, nor the ſame man in his ſeveral humors; ſo humorous and vain a thing is man.</p>
            <p n="39">39. Let the Exclaimer and Excepter (by imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) place himſelf in the Government, and caſt how to come off without caſting, ſo with honour in corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponding
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151178:13"/>
it wiſely with other States and Princes, and giving his own people content, let him preſent before him the continual Suits and Petitions of different Sects and parties, and that he is never free from complaints of one nature or other, nor from Viſits and Addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to and from Forraign States and Princes, or his own people; how alſo he is never quit nor quiet from clamors and exclamations of croſt parties, that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, nor in juſtice may not comply to; then likewiſe, the continual dangers that attend him from the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengeful, envious, and hateful, as any way croſt, or not complyed to; and how he cannot pleaſe any, though he endeavour to pleaſe all; ſo that ſurpriſals do continually haunt him, by reaſon whereof he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have time to come off in his thoughts and cares about the aforeſaids; and a world of things more, which much check him in his recreations and refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſo in his retreats; beſides the awe and fear of trecherous ſurpriſals: Surely all things afore fully pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to him, would awe and affright him from ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proching the <hi>Throne,</hi> and go near to cauſe him to <hi>Reproach</hi> it.</p>
            <p n="40">40. Take up <hi>Arms</hi> then (if <hi>Arms</hi> you will take up) even with your Enemy (as you eſteem and call him) ſeeing he ſides with, and protects your friend, yea your ſelf, and your Mother, your Country, that bare you, and brought you up, yea oppoſe with him your dear friend, your King, ſo called; for your Kings ſake, your Country, and for ſhame be no longer be-foold with pretenſes, hopes, and promiſes of Caſtles in the Ayr, and aery <hi>Utopia</hi>'s; nor with ſmiles and ſalutes of <hi>how doſt my Brother?</hi> and by and by you are thrild or ſmit under the fifth rib; remember all the hazards you
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151178:14"/>
undergo at Sect. 34. ſo divers other places, and for fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, compreſs and comply, and do no more ſo, and ſo recover your ſelves like men; for I will aſſure you, you now act like children, babes, and ſucklings.</p>
            <p n="41">41. Its our wiſeſt courſe then to comply to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Government, and ſo ſettle an Agreement amongſt our ſelves, to prevent diviſions; for there is no likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of bettering our ſelves, had we free liberty to do it, but of ruine rather; and did Forraign Princes and States ſee us ſo ſetled, it would ſtave them off from attempting on us, and ſo ſecure us, and enable us to attempt on them, eſpecially on thoſe that have wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us, and will not right us, &amp;c. But</p>
            <p n="42">42. I will now make head againſt all excepters and objectors whatſoever againſt his Highneſs as an Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and ſo to have no right to the Government, &amp;c. which is ſufficiently done in our <hi>Army Armed,</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector Protected,</hi> with what elſe is (for ought I know) objectable againſt him; but I will (with addition of this) fortifie it (I hope) paſt forfeiting &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="43">43. Be then ingenious, upright, and fair condition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (my Reader) I pray thee, and do as thou wouldſt be done to; ceaſe judging, cenſuring, and condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, till thou haſt ſeen what's ſaid in his behalf; and then let not the paſſions of partiality, love or hate, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacle ingenious, judgement, but come off like a man, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Let it be remembred then, that when the Lord <hi>Fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fax</hi> declin'd going againſt the <hi>Scot,</hi> his Highneſs being then in <hi>Ireland,</hi> whither he was ſent to curb that ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born and rebellious people, which (<hi>Caeſar</hi>-like, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like himſelf) he did in a trice, preventing <hi>veni, vidi, vici,</hi> with <hi>vici</hi> only, he was then ſent for, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151178:14"/>
choſen by the ſaid Parliament to undertake againſt the <hi>Scot;</hi> which he did with the like ſucceſs and ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, all things conſidered; his Highneſs was then alſo inveſted with the <hi>Militia</hi> or Sword, as <hi>Defender</hi> of the three Nations, which is in nature <hi>Protector,</hi> yea King, as ſo ſelf-ly ſworded, and as ſo choſen by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he was choſen and impowred (as afore) by the whole Nation, each individual therein, as in the <hi>Army Armed,</hi> and <hi>Protector Protected,</hi> is fully ſet out, and made good againſt all oppoſers and objecters, be whom they will, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="45">45. Again, his Right of Turn and place choſe him, for he was next in place to the ſaid Lord <hi>Fairfax;</hi> ſo it had been injuſtice and a diſhonour to him to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd him, and incline to any other, without juſt cauſe of exception, as unable, or unfaithful, or ſhort of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficientcies to undergo; but his apparent perfections, and the Parliaments continued choice employments of him, ſpake and evidenced for him as afore.</p>
            <p n="46">46. His own known worth of Wiſdom and Care, Fortitude and good Fortune choſe him (had the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment not choſe him) as the hopefulleſt to preſerve, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, and protect our Countries.</p>
            <p n="47">47. His own, ſo his Souldiers Honors and Safeties choſe him, and would have juſtified an uſurpation, and retenſion, (as call'd) til ſecured againſt after claps of diſpowering, and then of over-powering; and I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it had been <hi>Self</hi> and <hi>Publike</hi> Trechery, not to have ſo uſurped or aſſumed, alſo held the power, til he had throughly provided for his own and his Souldiers ſafety, as afore, ſo our Countries alſo what he could.</p>
            <p n="48">48. His Countries neceſſities choſe him, as in like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhood its moſt hopeful Deliverer, Defender, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151178:15"/>
by reaſon of his known perfections of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, wiſdom, fame, and fortitude; and theſe are beyond the giddy, the ignorant, the partial, and paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate, vocal, or articulate free choice of the people, as call'd: And this alone authoriſed <hi>Moſes</hi> to aſſume and hold the Government, for the Peoples ſafety &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="49">49. Laſtly, As ſo choſen and impowered by al afore, God alſo choſe him; for whom, or what Wiſdom, Reaſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Juſtice, Mercy, and juſt Neceſſity choſe, and allow of, God doth, muſt, and wil approve of, who is them al, &amp;c. ſo he is of God, and by Divine ordination, as wel as by humane; which alſo, yea therefore is alſo Divine, being as afore: So he is choſen by Divine and Humane ordination, the Governour of our three Countries, deny it who can: But for his Government, it concerns his Highneſs to look to it, for I meddle not with it, only his Right thereto; and I think I am right, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="50">50. The aforeſaids ſtanding clear and good, I ſay then, that reverence, love, and loyalty are his juſt dues, as to any King or Prince that ever was, as he is beyond them al in points of choice and deſert, as hath or ſhal appear: ſo alſo is a ſobriety in judging and cenſuring of him about things out of our reach, and out of his (oft-times) to act as he ſhould, or would; ſo many lets, and obſtacles of al ſorts Governours have, that they cannot as they ſhould, or would, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="51">51. It muſt not be forgot then that according to Sect. 44. his Highneſs is choſen and impowered with the univerſal Militia, and ſo King'd in power, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Law, and cuſtome of choice, as by the free Votes of the People, and I ſay ſomwhat beyond, in that way of choice, as choſen by a Parliament choſen
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151178:15"/>
by the People, who in reſpect of the rude multitude of the Country chuſers, are a company of wiſe and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men, having alſo al our other Arguments, that <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex</hi>-like, points and ſends them to him: Whereas in chuſing <hi>Parliaments</hi> or Kings, Princes, or Governours of Nations, or of any ſort, there is ſeldom knowledge of, or reſpect to perfections; but to partiality only; for the paſſions and affections of love and hate, fear and hope, friendſhip or relation to, ſo power, force, or fraud, and an hundred by and particular ends, as packt, hir'd and faction'd thereto, and not choiſeneſs, choſe, the choſen; yet this is call'd free choice, and the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the People ſo magnifi'd and cry'd up, but we muſt cry it down, for down it is in nature, though thus grac'd, I ſay then, that Licentiateneſs is not a liberty, but the only bondage; Were fitting <hi>Boundaries</hi> ſet for chooſing, to fetch in the Choice, the wiſe, worthy, and able, and keep out the worthleſs, &amp;c. alſo to keep the ſo choſen within their ſaid bounds, that they extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant not; I allow then of ſuch a Liberty, elſe not: But theſe uſeful Boundaries they would alſo cal Bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and a loſs of Liberty and Priviledges,; ſo it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that their Freedom is only Licentiateneſs, which is the only Bondage, as afore; and our Freedom is conducing Bindings, &amp;c. now how we ſhal agree, I know not, ſeeing we thus diſagree.</p>
            <p n="52">52. Things thus conſidered, ſhew me (if you can) the Man, the Parliament, King, Prince, or Power what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, ſo choſen in al particulars, &amp;c. but I know you cannot; however, he is ſo choſen the higheſt Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour (if the juſt and univerſal Sword be Supreme or higheſt) as clearly ſhews his Right, and quits him of Uſurpation, and enjoyns al ſorts to obedience, and al
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151178:16"/>
the Duties at Sect. 50. And that's enough to make good our <hi>Aſſertion,</hi> and yet the Deſertleſs would deſert him, though thus <hi>aſserted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have yet ſomthing alſo to ſay concerning the Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> which ſeems to ſuit with this point: Know then, that when the ſaid Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> had the univerſal Militia or Power in his Power, and that the Parliament and City bandyed againſt him and the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, to disband them, and in concluſion riſe in Arms to enforce it; he held his Power, for his own and his Souldiers Honours and Safety, ſo for his Countries; and finding himſelf in plight to put them to it, did ſo, and to make ſhort, came in like a Conquerour, yet as conquered, with Modeſty and Mildneſs; for what <hi>Lex talionis</hi> would have allowed him to do to ſuch as would have undone him, and alſo endangered the Nation to ruinous Diviſion, let Juſtice her ſelf judge; conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that both He and the Army had been moſt faithful and valiant in behalf of them and our Country. But I take it that it was only the<note place="margin">The Pulpits In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiary I take it, makes this good.</note> Presbyterial party of the Parliament, ſo of the Clergy and City, that incenſed the people againſt him, not for the common good ſake, but their own ends only, as that the Presbyterie might Prelate it under the Notion of Prieſts, and ſo cruſh all other Sects in Religion (as call'd) but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,<note place="margin">The name of Presbyterie is not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive to me, but their natures of Pride and Pretences, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce contention. Rom. <hi>14.</hi> ſo nor Reaſon allow not the ſword but the ſword of the Spirit; and yet the ſword alſo againſt Invaders of the Fundamentals, ſo the Peoples peace, &amp;c.</note> the only Sect, as out, or againſt Religion, if ſuch a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment be againſt it, and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs in that point for it. However it appeared that he was a Prince in juſt Power, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo uſed it Prince-like, as defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151178:16"/>
and not offenſively; alſo for juſt Self and Publike ends, and this he might, and ſo may any; for its the end of Power ſo to do: To wiſe eyes he was <hi>Roy</hi> in Right of Might and juſt Power, if uſed as afore, and the Parliament but his <hi>Vice-Roys,</hi> and did act only on their <hi>bene geſſere,</hi> and his <hi>bene placitum</hi> or permiſſion, for what he then did, he could always have done, and might, on our premiſſes, elſe not; but ſupport them rather, as the end of juſt Power is both to ſupport and ſuppreſs,<note place="margin">Wherein came he ſhort in that little brunt of his Highneſs? How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he ſhewed by that Act, what he might, and would, as he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, conducing, and as juſtly neceſſitated: and ſo would my Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepter do, if in their place, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentinely ſave his head, and his head his Country, &amp;c.</note> as the general or juſt particulars neceſſitate; why elſe is't a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er but for ſuch ends? For can any one in reaſon think that juſt power impowered for that end; or however, being in Nature, Reaſon, and Religion, bound to right what they can the wronged, whether Individuals, or the Univerſal; as did <hi>Moſes</hi> in both: who though not formally impowered, yet having <hi>Power,</hi> righted his individual wrong'd brother, and next, his Brethren the People: and ſo may any, with our cautions, princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and premiſes, elſe not. Can then I ſay ſuch Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſee themſelves unjuſtly and inhumanly acted againſt for all their Humanities, which rather cal for Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes; and <hi>Gratias,</hi> inſtead of ſuch ingratitude? and yet like ſenſleſs Momes, ſit ſtil; it cannot be. Can they alſo ſee their Country neglected, as not acted for, as it ought; or acted againſt, as it ought not; and like the ſenſleſs ſit ſtil? it cannot be: However it ought not be;<note place="margin">Hints or memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randums.</note> but they may (<hi>Moſes</hi>-like) without our Cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, act againſt ſuch Actors; yet not without our Cautions, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:151178:17"/>Subordinate Swords and Powers have their Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, or the Supreme to awe and command them, and enforce a rendition of their Powers; but the Supreme is King in Nature, and asks more then Grace to govern it; and its wel if any way governed: For who ſhal ſay to the King<note place="margin">Or any higheſt Power, in point of Power.</note> what doſt thou?</p>
            <p>Capitulate not then (oh thou naked Man) petulantly and daringly with the Brandiſht and Flaming Blade, or Univerſal Sword or Power, leſt it ſanguine it ſelf in thy <hi>Sanguis;</hi> but rather Serpent-like, ſave thy Head, ſo thy Feet, yea thy whole Body, by thy applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to our application and addreſment, elſe al thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended courage and faithfulneſs to the cauſe, are but fooliſh and vain-glorious follies, as inſenſibleneſs, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, and ſtubbornneſs, inſteed of reſolution and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage for &amp;c. To what end ſhould a <hi>Venice</hi> glaſs ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapertly juſtle it, or contend with an Iron pot? except in our way of Oratory, of Reaſon, and Humanity: As ſpare me (oh noble Sir, I pray you) for I am too weak and brittle to deal with you, ſo chuſe rather to Incumbe, then try it out with ſuch a <hi>Combahant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Al Powers (though unjuſt) wil yet if they can, Rule, and not be Rul'd, and that oft-times unjuſtly; but if juſtly (though unjuſt) happy are the Rul'd: But juſt Powers may according to juſtice and juſt neceſſities, rule and over-rule. Know then that juſt or unjuſt Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers (though a little unjuſt) are Juſt; for God himſelf found folly in Heaven amongſt his Angels &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The King himſelf was of our Judgement, and we of his: That to part with the Militia, was to part with <hi>Abiſhag</hi> his Miſtris, for the Kingdom followed it, cauſe it un-king'd him, and King'd his un-kingers in point of Power: and asſo, of al things <hi>ad placitum,</hi> the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151178:17"/>
impowering his Highneſs,<note place="margin">In power.</note> 
               <hi>King</hi>-like, left him to himſelf, in point of Power to govern if he would, or ſee juſt cauſe, which he may with our Principles and premiſes of juſt neceſſities and conducings, as afore; and as did and might the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> on the ſame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count: for none muſt be ſo ſilly as to think that the univerſal Power wil (if it can help it) be overpowered<note place="margin">It may abide perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but no compulſive In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion, eſpecially to unjuſt ſufferings and dangers.</note>; whatever in a wiſe policy, it may connive, pretend, and comply to, and it comes off honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, fairly, and wel, if with a little wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, al things conſidered, for ſo Angels wil do: Thus the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> did no wrong; or if any, but little, alſo as of neceſſity inforced thereto; but wiſely Sentinel'd and Perdu'd it to prevent Surpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals, and the better to ſurprize his Surprizers.</p>
            <p>And the Parliament as afore outing the King, and his Seed, and immediately inveſting his Highneſs with the Militia, the Kings <hi>Abiſhag</hi> or Miſtris, or rather, with the Kingdom it ſelf, he ſucceeds the King as the next Man, by an Act<note place="margin">As their doings, which they never undid.</note> of Parliament, as Governour in point of Power, either in <hi>Eſſe, Poſſe,</hi> or <hi>Potentia;</hi> and thus (beſides al other Arguments, he claims Right to the Government; and if he Governs as he hath done, and promiſeth to do, and provide alſo as we have hinted, we are happy, and he is worthy of the <hi>Government,</hi> and We unworthy of ſuch a Governour.</p>
            <p n="53">53. But ſure for this my doing I ſhal not ſcape cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring as a <hi>Flatterer,</hi> a Time-ſerver, &amp;c. in this <hi>Tract,</hi> &amp;c. I cannot deny but ſo it may be, but I do deny that ſo it is: Now who is't can conclude from poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, to certainties, as that things are, cauſe they may
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151178:18"/>
be; which as they cannot ſay, they ſay nothing; for I can from poſſibilities (if they be good Arguments) make guilty the moſt innocent, &amp;c. But the Laws of <hi>Logick</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> ſo of Civility, Humanity, and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity are againſt ſuch concluſions, and in doubtfuls for the contrary, &amp;c. as for the faireſt and moſt friendly conſtruction; which to make good, I have and do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you alſo with many allowable reaſons and grounds for what I do; and do here ſeriouſly and ingeniouſly proteſt, that I would not have ſet Pen to Paper, but to diſcover falſhood, and make Truth apparent; for there is no reaſon that his <hi>Highneſs</hi> ſhould be wrong'd or cenſur'd as an Uſurper, beſides many other unjuſt Objections and Exceptions againſt him; and the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers go clear away, as juſt and true in the ſame; and his <hi>Highneſs</hi> remain as guilty, to his great diſhonour: for Untruths in point of judgement do as much abuſe, as do thoſe of relation; for the people miſled in either, are thereby incenſed againſt his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> as if guilty, &amp;c. ſo fal to factioning it for and againſt, to the endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering of all, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="54">54. Nor may the cenſure of <hi>Flattery,</hi> nor any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pravings, &amp;c. obſtacle or check duties of any nature, eſpecially of ſo high concernment, for ſo no good thing almoſt wil be done, and many <hi>evils</hi> muſt be done; for there is not any good thing but may be vilified and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved; nor any bad, but may be rendred ſpeciouſly good &amp;c. Let the <hi>Performer</hi> then ſtand clear in his own heart and Conſcience, and ſo reſt reſolved for the reſt, elſe farewel al goodneſs and good things, if we be afraid of <hi>Sanballats Foxes,</hi> who would demoliſh <hi>good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> it ſelf, they are ſo <hi>Bad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 55. You are contented that I do my <hi>Country</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:151178:18"/>
al the good ſervice I can, but you except that I plead thus for the <hi>Protector,</hi> alſo you would not have me to hint nor minde him of theſe his Rights, &amp;c, for it wil pride him, and he is proud enough already.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If it be any factious Incendiaries or trouble-States that object thus, I anſwer, Why except they at what they are the Cauſers of? For had they not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered our Country by crying up the King of <hi>Scots</hi> Rights, and crying down the Lord Protectors, and ſo divided and factioned the people to the Hazard and Ruine of al, I had been ſilent; ſo they clearly excuſe me, and condemn themſelves of what they accuſe me of, by neceſſitating me to do it. Whoever elſe objects, I conceive this anſwer wil ſatisfie them alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 56. But its objected, That the <hi>Law</hi> makes this or that not <hi>Treaſon,</hi> except againſt a <hi>King,</hi> nor bindes, except for a King, &amp;c. ſo ſuch are not Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, nor capable of Tryal as ſuch, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If ſo, I know not what to ſay to ſuch a Law, nor ſuch Lawyers; and yet they ſhal know by and by, that I know what to ſay to both, ſo care for neither of them in this caſe.</p>
            <p>By this alſo (it may be) they wil ſay, that the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament could not, nor can his Highneſs now, make <hi>Laws</hi> or <hi>Ordinances</hi> without a King, &amp;c. Oh the force that is in words, ceremonies, and opinion: But we ſhal ſhew by and by that our Principle is too hard for them al, as wel as for al at Sect. 16.</p>
            <p>However they wil by this (if ſo) enforce his <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> to <hi>King</hi> it in Title, to entitle him to the aforeſaids. But we wil take to pieces theſe poſitions, and examine them, &amp;c. ſo ſhal we ſee what confeſſion they wil make.</p>
            <p n="57">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:151178:19"/>57. If as againſt the King be Treaſon, what then is it againſt the Kings <hi>King?</hi> Sure the greater is greater then the leſs, and contains it; Now whether the <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> welfare and ſafety be not greater then <hi>Charls Stuart</hi>'s Right, if Right, ſee Sect. 3. to 17. Then whether <hi>Salus</hi> be not highly concern'd in the preſent <hi>Governour</hi> thereof, ſee Sect. 28. &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="58">58. Note, our Principle, <hi>Kings</hi> the higheſt <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> in point of Power (however cald or entituled) in al things, as <hi>Salus</hi> is neceſſitated, or juſtly conduc'd to, eſpecially in point of Safety, ſo his own ſafety in relation thereto; ſo that as afore, neither Words, nor Letters, nor no Law for, or if againſt, nor any thing is valuable or pleadable in oppoſition thereto; elſe the aforeſaids were higher then the higheſt; to which all at Sect. 16. ſtoop, yeild, and comply; yet ſome of our Laws and Lawyers (as afore) are lawleſs, and wil not, ſo muſt be out-law'd, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="59">59. What's the word <hi>King,</hi> but a compoſition of Letters in themſelves nothing; for to people of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther language, they are only <hi>ſounds,</hi> &amp;c. ſo the power of the word is in thy conception or opinion of it, or of cuſtome; but the right power is in the extent of juſt power; next, in the worth and perfections of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon impowered: See then what moſt <hi>Kings</hi> are, at Sect. 51. to 52. and ſee what his <hi>Highneſs</hi> is at Sect. 4. to 5. and ſo who then are Kings.</p>
            <p n="60">60. His Highneſs hath the <hi>Militia</hi> of three Nations in his hand, Doth this, or the Title <hi>King,</hi> King? Next, he is choſen in points of choice, beyond all or moſt Kings or Governours, as afore; alſo hath choice parts: Kings theſe, or the Title <hi>King?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="61">61. Is a King of <hi>Scotland</hi> alone, cauſe call'd and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony'd
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151178:19"/>
like a King, ſuch a King as is the Protector of our three Nations?</p>
            <p n="62">62. There was no King in Iſrael, &amp;c. There was then to be none, for they never had any; What's then the Meaning, but that there was no Univerſal <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> at that time? Governour then is the <hi>Genus,</hi> and ſo contains all <hi>Species</hi> or kinds of <hi>Governours,</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever call'd; which howſoever in point of <hi>Species,</hi> he is yet a Governour or Ruler in the <hi>Genus:</hi> Thus <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, Captains, Prieſts, Prophets</hi> and <hi>Kings,</hi> at different times King'd it in <hi>Genus</hi> and <hi>Species,</hi> though not alike <hi>ſpeciouſly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="63">63. <hi>Treaſon</hi> then againſt the <hi>King,</hi> was not as he was a ſingle Man, or as call'd <hi>King,</hi> but as he was the <hi>Univerſal Governour,</hi> in whoſe ſafety the <hi>Peoples</hi> ſafety was concerned: It was not Treaſon as it related to words, expreſſions, or Titles, but to his place or office, and its relate, the people as afore.</p>
            <p n="64">64. Let the Lord <hi>Protector</hi> then have what name or Title you pleaſe, it matters not, he is a King in nature, as well as the reſt, or beſt; However, as he is the Univerſal <hi>Governour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thirty two Kings as call'd, and Tranſlated, <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua</hi> ſlew on this ſide <hi>Jor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan;</hi> they were (I believe) but the higheſt Governours of Cities. I think the <hi>L. Mayor</hi> of <hi>London</hi> is for h<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> time as good as the beſt of them.</note> in whoſe ſafety <hi>Salus</hi> ſafety is concern'd, this and that, or what was Treaſon to the <hi>King</hi> ſo call'd, is the ſame to him at leaſt, he being more &amp;c. its <hi>Treaſon</hi> then to the Publike for any to attempt upon, or againſt her Higheſt or Chiefeſt <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Defender,</hi> or <hi>Protector,</hi> to the endangering her Protection, Welfare, and Safety.</p>
            <p n="66">66. Its conſiderable alſo that <hi>Law</hi> hath two parts, <hi>viz.</hi> its <hi>Ceremonials,</hi> and its <hi>Eſſentials,</hi> &amp;c. its <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monials</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:151178:20"/>
are words, expreſſions, and names, ſo alſo ſuch and ſuch ways, courſes and forms to proceed by &amp;c. its Eſſentials are Juſtice, Rights, and Safety, of which this laſt is firſt; ſo in competition, Juſtice and Rights muſt comply to Safety, &amp;c. If the Eſſentials muſt comply to <hi>Safety,</hi> what then can the Ceremonies of Law in juſt competition with its <hi>Lord,</hi> the <hi>Peoples Safety,</hi> ſay to it? What reaſon have they, or is it igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, obſtinacy, or wilfulneſs, &amp;c. Muſt the Lord, the Publike Welfare, be a ſervant to its ſervants? Yea, be deſtroyed by them? <hi>viz.</hi> by words and names, ſo by manners and ways of proceeding; Ceremonials all to the Eſſentials afore, the Eſſentials at Sect. 16. in competition comply, but our Trivials are very trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome.</p>
            <p n="67">67. Remember then as afore, that the Higheſt Governour, as <hi>Salus,</hi> is concern'd and neceſſitated, is not bound to Law it ſelf, much leſs to Lawyers, or any Ceremonials; for in behalf of <hi>Salus,</hi> he is Judge and Lord of the Law as is conducing.</p>
            <p n="68">68. Elſe as afore, how could <hi>Salus</hi> on exigents be ſaved or provided for, if words and letters ſay nay, and none might gainſay them.</p>
            <p n="71">71. So may he act, alſo do and undo, without, yea againſt Law, yea Law it ſelf, much more Laws, Letters, which are oft great lets to its intention, as the Publike is juſtly neceſſitated, cauſe the Publike is Lord of the Law, and who made it for its own end, and not againſt, and if in error or accident it be againſt, it muſt be made to know its place, is to give place.</p>
            <p n="72">72. Well, but yet ye are not at quiet, but are much troubled at one thing, you would fain be free <hi>Engliſh</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and not under the <hi>Sword,</hi> nor <hi>Taxes.</hi> Be it ſo,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151178:20"/>
Give then theſe <hi>Weaklings</hi> their wils, &amp;c. ſo the Army is diſarmed, and Taxes diſcharg'd, and now I hope we ſhal hear no more news of you, and yet what means this noiſe, this clattering of Armour and Weapons, this thundering of Canons and other ſhot, this boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and running of rampant Horſemen to and fro, what theſe ſhriekings and cryings out of all ſorts? Whence theſe ſtreams of Blood? How came theſe mangled and ſlain Carcaſſes? Whence thoſe frighted Fugitives? What's the matter of this ſmoak, fire, and flame? &amp;c. Surely from hence all, Your Army diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, the <hi>Hydra Faction</hi> hath charged you with ten Armies for that one, and ſo overcharg'd you; for now <hi>Royaliſts,</hi> Peers, Prelates, and Prieſts, ſo Lawyers and Goſpellers of all ſorts and faſhions, yea every ſeveral Sect, Church, and Faction are in Arms to offend one another, and defend themſelves, and to Rule and Soveraignize it if they can; and <hi>Forreigners</hi> hearing thereof, take the advantage, and ſtrike in amongſt them, and whil'ſt your ſelves fight for the bone, the ſtranger <hi>Doegs</hi> may chance get it; however, the Land may be ruin'd before it be righted, or recovered by any ſide. All theſe miſeries, and this our bondage, your licentiate liberty, your freedom hath brought us to, which the bondage of an Army and Taxes would have freed us from, and now you wiſh (when too late) oh that the <hi>Army</hi> were on <hi>foot</hi> again to ſave our <hi>Heads,</hi> &amp;c. and for <hi>Taxes,</hi> you would rather then fail take the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels</hi> counſel, part with all rather then your lives, or rather then Husbands and Wives, Parents and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, alſo near and dear friends and Kindred ſhould be parted by ſlaughters and maſſacrings, or ſo mangled and made away, and your ſelves live a dying life of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151178:21"/>
grief, care, miſery, nakedneſs and want, even to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual expiring.</p>
            <p n="73">73. Had the poor <hi>Savoyans</hi> had a protecting, a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending Army (which could they have been in ſeaſon aware of) ſure they would, alſo have taxt themſelves according to the <hi>Divels</hi> Doctrine, rather then come under the hands and Paws of ſuch Divels, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="74">74. Lets know then your minds in ſeaſon, whether you will have any protecting Armies by Sea and Land, Brave Royal and Imperial Forces or no, to ſave you from Royaliſts, and the reſt, that ſo we may know how to pleaſe you, though we pleaſe you not.</p>
            <p n="75">75. That the King of <hi>Scots</hi> as call'd hath no right to the Government, is without any more adoe apparent in nature and reaſon, from what is already ſaid, to any common underſtanding almoſt, how then to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive, as having (contrary to the very end, uſe, and being of Governours) ſided with his <hi>Father</hi> againſt his <hi>Mother,</hi> his <hi>Country,</hi> in tranſcendent trecheries, &amp;c. and that his <hi>Father</hi> was highly trecherous to his truſt, appears by the Lord <hi>Chief Juſtice Cook</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> his <hi>Kings Caſe,</hi> heard, accepted, and confirmed by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, on which the King was executed by their order; beſides his oft needleſs and cauſleſs oppreſſion of the People, as appears at Sect. 95.</p>
            <p n="76">76. Again, the Parliament made an Act againſt any of that Race for ever being <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Governours</hi> of this <hi>Nation</hi> &amp;c. and this as the whole Body of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple was contracted in them, they might do; ſo may they make or marr any other Laws, as conduceth to the Peoples Welfare and Safety, as they have that of ten pounds in the hundred to eight, and then to ſix pounds for uſe monies, which if they find amiſs, they
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:151178:21"/>
may alter again, and advance it to what degree they find it capable of, or depreſs it as they pleaſe; As the Hollanders, and other Countries, raiſe, and raze their exchange moneys, as avails to the Publike: Our Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple will juſtifie it alſo, and what not?</p>
            <p n="77">77. In ſhort, as they may make one Law, ſo may they many, or any, and as they may marr, alter, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>make one, or more, ſo may they <hi>ad infinitum,</hi> as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth to the Publike; for the Power that impowered them for the leaſt, or any, influenc'd them for all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducings, and againſt all ſeducings, of which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that Race to to reign here was one; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they arraigned one, and raz'd out the reſt. So by all our Arguments his Highneſs is the next man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo choſen as afore.</p>
            <p n="78">78. Now whatever Ordinance or Act the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made againſt any one Univerſal Governour for future, yet if afore, or afterward, they have impow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ered the Lord Protector with the univerſal Militia of our three Nations or Countries, as their Defender and Protector, and ſo left him, and ſo he ſtill ſtands, beſides all our other ways of Choice and Inveſture of him, in caſe they had not ſo done, they for their parts by ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (beſides what we have ſaid and done) have to our beſt underſtanding poſtured him in the place, and condition he now ſtands, for all the ſaid Act: for if in words, or by an Ordinance or Act they ſay, we will not for future have any one alone univerſal Governour more, &amp;c. and yet afore, or then, or after, gave him the triple, or threefold Militia, they King'd him in point of Power, call him as you pleaſe; and they were ſo King'd themſelves by the People, though not ſo call'd, and yet call'd ſo by a King<note place="margin">K. James</note>, for to ſay in words, or by an
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:151178:22"/>
Act of Parliament, We will not that any one man rule as afore, &amp;c. and yet in actions do it, which are more real, alſo of later edition, and ſo more authentick, as ſeeming to revoke what they ſaid; and is as much as to ſay, we are now of another mind and judgement, and will have this Gentleman however to Rule and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern for his time, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="79">79. Yet we humbly make bold to ſay, that it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns his <hi>Highneſs</hi> of his own goodneſs, nobleneſs, and ingenuity, and for his Honour and Renown ſake, to make good what he can the ends of ſuch a be-truſt, as the welfare of the People, and their Safety, &amp;c. and to conſider of our contents, and in ſeaſon to provide accordingly, &amp;c. However, his Highneſs Rights as afore, I am forc'd to make good, for our former rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſake; alſo to prevent and affront the Invaders thereof, to our endangering to ruine.</p>
            <p n="80">80. <hi>Object.</hi> But it may be ſaid, this impowering him as afore, was only a be-truſt, &amp;c. a redelivery being expected when exacted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> So was the <hi>Parliaments</hi> from the <hi>People,</hi> a be-truſt, as on intention and expectation of a rendition, &amp;c. But thoſe <hi>Mortals</hi> would have immortaliz'd it, and might with our cautions, ſo the Arguments are <hi>idem,</hi> though not<note place="margin">The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament by reaſon of their diviſions, had oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite ends and could not mind the main.</note> 
               <hi>ad idem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, a <hi>Betrust</hi> is anſwered; as the <hi>main ends</hi> of it are anſwered, the <hi>Peoples Safety,</hi> &amp;c. And here I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniouſly proteſt, I ſee not but that his <hi>Highneſs</hi> hath, doth, and will as faithfully and ſufficiently quit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as I conceive any can, or would do that ſhould poſſeſs that place, ſay <hi>Praters</hi> what they pleaſe, and if he ſhall pleaſe to make good our <hi>Contents</hi> as afore, he would <hi>Crown</hi> us, and we ſhould then do well to do as
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:151178:22"/>
much by him, for we cannot do too much for our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,</hi> as we cannot for our <hi>Saviour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="82">82. However, I conceive, yea I think that I may ſafely <hi>poſitive</hi> it, and ſay, that neither his <hi>Highneſs</hi> to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> nor the <hi>Parliament</hi> to the <hi>People,</hi> might part with their <hi>Powers</hi> or Commiſſions, but on our cautions at Sect. 47. and that their engagements and be-truſts forbade and charged them to the contrary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But its urg'd that his <hi>Highneſs</hi> was the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments</hi> ſervant<note place="margin">So was the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, ſo the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is the ſame.</note>, ſo ought to obey, and deliver up his <hi>Power</hi> when called for, it being only a be-truſt, alſo he promiſed ſo to do, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>For the Truth of this, that none may be deceived, I will ſet it right, and then leave it to judgement: I ſay then,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I deny that he was the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſervant, and if he was, I care not; ſo nor for his promiſe, if any, and as its ſaid, to be a Be-truſt, ſee Sect. 80.</p>
            <p>Are the <hi>Servants</hi> of a <hi>Lords Family</hi> the Stewards, cauſe the <hi>Steward</hi> entertains them, and takes them in, ſeeing he pays them out of his <hi>Lords</hi> Treaſury? Are they not both (though differently degree'd) <hi>ſervants</hi> to one and the ſame <hi>Lord?</hi> in oppoſition or competition, then who ſhall the meaneſt ſervant comply to? Yea may not the caſe be ſuch, as that he ought not obey, but with reſpectiveneſs (if he have power) ſoberly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Steward in his Lords behalf, and for his own ſafety, if he find that he endanger either? But you will ſay, who ſhall be Judge? for any one may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, &amp;c. For this, ſee Sect. 83. and then Judge you.</p>
            <p>Nor may the Stewards own ſervants, as may not the Lords own ſervants, ſo nor the Kings, when he
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:151178:23"/>
was, be true to, or ſide with, or obey their own <hi>Maſters</hi> in oppoſition to their grand Maſter, the <hi>Publike;</hi> This the <hi>Parliament,</hi> ſo that next afore, judg'd on the <hi>ſervants</hi> ſide, when it came to be agitated afore them, and ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd of the <hi>ſervants</hi> or <hi>ſubjects</hi> judgement and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and puniſht thoſe as <hi>Traytors</hi> that were true to their private Maſter or Truſt, againſt their grand Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, the <hi>Publike:</hi> ſee our Sect. 63. as afore, for judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>If alſo neither the promiſes, nor the ſacred vows of a <hi>Wife</hi> cannot binde her to God, in oppoſition of her <hi>Husbands</hi> Rights, cauſe obedience is better then ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and for that ſhe is not a <hi>ſelf-power,</hi> as is a <hi>Widow,</hi> who may vow, and if vow, muſt perform; but a <hi>Wife</hi> might ſoon be head her <hi>Head,</hi> with ſuch pretenſes and licenciate ſervices, &amp;c. ſo nor can Magiſtrates, Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, nor any Powers make a vow, promiſe, or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant amongſt our ſelves, but if it prove endanger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or deſtructive to the Publike, which is our Lord and Husband, and the ſupreme <hi>Lex,</hi> to which we are ſubordinate, but it may be renounc'd: In our own concernments we may promiſe, vow, and keep, elſe not, and yet not deſtructives, or endangerings to ruine, but what have we to do to binde others, how then our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne the Publike, whom we are bound to unbinde,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But who ſhall judge of all, is a main question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="83">83. This (hitherto) hath been a troubleſome and puzzling queſtion; and the <hi>Queſtioniſt</hi> applauds him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for wiſe, learned, knowing, and able, though a weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, if he can but poſe his <hi>Adverſary,</hi> who might have poſed him, had he firſt asked the <hi>Queſtion,</hi> however both ſides are <hi>Dilemma'd,</hi> and ſtand poſtur'd like <hi>Lots</hi> Wife, or as two ſilent Statues, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:151178:23"/>Now ſeeing none of our <hi>Magies,</hi> either of <hi>Layicks</hi> or <hi>Levites, Lawyers</hi> or <hi>Goſpellers,</hi> of any kinde, name, nature, or degree,<note place="margin">I have heard them thus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver read any of them.</note> no not the occularly conſpicuous <hi>Cardinals,</hi> as call'd; nor the notion'd, ſublime, or Seraphick <hi>Doctor,</hi> nor the <hi>Sentential Master</hi> have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd this, ſince the world was a world, ſo that it ſtill puzzleth all ſorts; it falls to the ſhare of the poor and illiterate, and therefore deſpicable Carpenters ſon to eſſay it, and ſo to venture beyond his <hi>Ne plus ultra;</hi> which he doth, as ſo conſtrained — Courteous Gentlemen and Readers, both this, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers other things in this book with an awful remiſneſs, and a wary fear; wherein if he err, or fail, ſo might, ſo do the <hi>Cardinals,</hi> and the <hi>Seraphicks</hi> aforeſaid, and in this they are <hi>errant,</hi> in that they attempt not at all to give ſatisfaction, alſo not ſufficiently (being <hi>Magies</hi>) to quit diſ-ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We ſay then as followeth,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Law,</hi> and <hi>Lawyers</hi> are concluſive Judges of what is within the circuit and precinct of their <hi>Jurisdiction,</hi> yet Appeals may be to Higher Courts, or to the <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery,</hi> or to the higheſt Judge, or Lord <hi>Chancellor,</hi> at Sect. 3. 5, 6. following; and again, for judgment on any of their judgements, ſee Sect. 7. except taken out of their hands in ſeaſon, and referr'd, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Arbytrators,</hi> or any truſted or referr'd to, though injudicious, yea injurious, are yet concluding Judges; yet we may as at firſt judge of their judgement, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Parliament</hi> are concluding Judges (when in being) for the <hi>Publike,</hi> and for particulars alſo, if re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd to, but all may as at 6, 7. on their judgements.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Yet any who is impowered, or hath power, and will conducingly and ſavingly improve it, as did <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:151178:24"/>
ſo according to our cautions is a <hi>Judge,</hi> a <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> for the <hi>Publike good,</hi> in oppoſition to any indangerings, or too much ſufferings by or from any; and who ſhall <hi>Judge</hi> of this, ſee Sect. 6, 7. both for concluſive and incluſive judgings, &amp;c. in ſhort, Power will be Judge, concludingly; but ought not abuſe their power, yet they may be judg'd on.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The <hi>Parliament</hi> not being, then the <hi>Higheſt publike Magiſtrate, King,</hi> or <hi>Protector,</hi> as you pleaſe, with their wiſe and faithful Councel (if for the <hi>Publike)</hi> are Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es concluſive, ſo for <hi>Individuals,</hi> if he pleaſe, yet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Law,</hi> except referr'd to; or if Law be Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, as dubious, or its Letter ridged, againſt juſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, or right Reaſon, he as higheſt Lord Chancellor, with his wiſe Councel, may catechiſe and chaſtiſe it, and always accept its dubious acceptations, with the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maneſt conſtructions; for ſuch is or ſhould be Lawyers and Laws ayms, and intentions, for ſuch are their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Juſt neceſſities (<hi>private</hi> or <hi>publike</hi>) allow any man, yea a <hi>ſervant</hi> over his Maſter, to turn <hi>Judge</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> for the preſent, if he will venture to put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf on the judgement of <hi>Law,</hi> and its Iſſue, or refer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to thoſe it concerns, to ſuffer if he have offended; here it concerns him, or any one, well to open and ſtate their cauſe apparently in each particular, and ſo refer and appeal, or abide the Tryal, and its iſſue; or who hath power or might to act ſo, ought ſtate his caſe right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and then appeal in point of Right, as at 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Note, all <hi>ſorts</hi> may from all concluding <hi>Judges</hi> of what name, nature, kinde, or degree ſoever they be, appeal for judgement of their judgements, ſo for any actions, doings, things, ſayings, or cenſures, judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:151178:24"/>
or opinions, or diſputes, or controverſies, to any one, or more, or as we pleaſe, or <hi>univerſally</hi> to all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, rational, good, wiſe, and juſt men, of judicious underſtandings, to ſee how they will judge thereof, though we ſhould be concluded as afore; and this is as much as can be had.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Any one in their own concernments, though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicious, is a concluſive Judge, but any one as at 7. may judge of his judgement.</p>
            <p n="9">9. But as more, of the Publike are concern'd, then the Publike Magiſtrate for the Publike, and for Privates the Law &amp;c. as at Sect. 17. except they refer, are Judges concluſive, yet any may, as at 7.</p>
            <p n="10">10. The Higheſt <hi>Judge,</hi> who (like <hi>Moſes</hi>) makes other Judges to preſent him, and to ſupply his place as a <hi>Judge,</hi> for he judges by them, ſure he is a concluſive Judge then, as was <hi>Moſes,</hi> cauſe you cannot go higher then the higheſt, and may if he pleaſe, perſonally judge all, yet as at 5. afore, &amp;c. So will he alſo hear the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of thoſe Judges or Councellors, and from all, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whats uprighteſt and beſt, the beſt he can, &amp;c. and though in the integrity of his cauſe and proceedings he may like God at Sect. 89. appeal, yet will he not (if wiſe) diſpower himſelf till ſecurd, if then.</p>
            <p>Thus, we may hear, and be heard, and judge of one anothers judgements, though not concluſively, for the concluſive judgements are as afore.</p>
            <p>Now if the higheſt Judges at Sect. 3. 5. 10. deal amiſs with us, I know no better way to do good on them, ſafely and ſecurely, then as at Sect. 1, 2, 4. but if ſubordinates abuſe us, then to appeal to ſuperiors, or to the ſupreme, as the <hi>Chancery,</hi> or the <hi>Lord Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors,</hi> at 3. 5. 10. afore, &amp;c. and from thence to Sect. 7.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:151178:25"/>According to the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, a Maſter of a Family, though his wife, children, and ſervants, ſhould have right on their ſides, in point of reaſon, or the rationality of their judgements) yet his reaſon and judgement, or if you will call it, his Will and pleaſure in his own concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and affairs (as having right, juſtice, and equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty on his ſide) ſhall ſtand and conclude things for or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and diſpoſing, thus if he build a houſe, he may hear the judgements of the aforeſaids, or of any one, and it may be they may be more rational then is he, but they ſute not with his mind, will, nor way, ſo he will have it built to his own content, and this is his right and due; the like of any thing, as one is ſelf-ly or princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally impowered, and concerned, and that Law checks not; and if this Power were not, there would be no end of things for diſputes, oppoſitions and reaſonings, alſo authority and propriety would be overthrown; for if rational Right ſhould carry it againſt righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as againſt the rights of dues, juſtice, and proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, witty children and ſervants, ſo divers others might ſomtimes rule and govern their wiſer, or however, their more juſt Governours, and have thei will and way in whats their Parents, or their Maſters, or the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, or anothers proprieties and rights to order and diſpoſe, &amp;c. cauſe their judgements may chance to be better, though worſe, or not ſo good; as overthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing juſtice, authority, and propriety, to a confuſion of all, as is already done in moſt houſes, where under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of a Religious Conſcience,<note place="margin">As not knowing his power &amp; place.</note> the witty and wily Wife, Children, and Servants, go ſeveral ways, and leave the weak Maſter maſterleſs; but let all ſuch know, that the Maſter of a Family, though he have failings, is King and Prieſt in his own houſe, to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:151178:25"/>
&amp;c. and he is a Judge and Reſolver of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence alſo in all indifferents in Religion to his own family, only Fundamentals muſt ſtand firm and fixt on all ſides, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but this is no place for this, but its worthy of a place and ſetling right, elſe it will unſettle Government, for the witty Govern'd will ſomtime govern their wiſer Governors, which muſt not be, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Note, None are concluding Judges where things come not under their command, nor are referr'd to them, though it be apparent that right is on ſuch ſide; Yet the Antagoniſt may ſtill vie it out, thus, two diſpute, but it relates to no concluding juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and refer it they will not, ſo the apparently vanquiſhed (though juſtly concluded againſt) yet cannot be concluded by any, but he may ſtill <hi>vie</hi> it out with his Antagoniſt, if he will, wilful it; but his Adverſary (though the other will not) may appeal to all ingenious and rational ſpirits, and ſo reſt ſatisfied, and anſwer the fool no longer in his folly. Thus much in point of Judging. We go on.</p>
            <p n="88">88. <hi>Law,</hi> the higheſt Governour is bound to, as he is only ſelf-ly concern'd, except juſtly neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which quits any one as well as himſelf, but as the <hi>Publike</hi> is concern'd in him, or any, or alone, he is not bound to it, for the <hi>Lord</hi> of the Law is Lawleſs.</p>
            <p n="89">89. If the Univerſal Publike Governour pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, judge, or deal amiſs, or contrary to his Be-truſt, its not well; but what ſhal we do with them more then with each poor Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytrator, ſo with Lawyers, Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Phyſitians &amp; Chyrurgions, who ſome of all of them at times<note place="margin">In points of Truſt, as by their ignorance, careleſneſs, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulneſs, ſo alſo by ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their intentional making preys and prizes on us, moſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly, oft beyond Tyrants, &amp;c.</note> abuſe
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:151178:26"/>
us as much, or more, as oft to loſs of life and eſtate, and our ſouls alſo; all which by ſo doing, forfeit their Be-truſts, and ſo their reputations; and yet we go on in truſting: in ſhort, we ſuffer more by them, yet ſay leſs.</p>
            <p>Truly I for my part know no better way for the <hi>People</hi> to deal with the higheſt <hi>Governour,</hi> then as I ſhall ſet out at the concluſion of this Book; nor for Governours that are of honour and integrity, then nobly for their Honours ſake to do as did <hi>Samuel</hi> of himſelf (for he was not call'd to accompt) nobly appeal to the people in point of his uprightneſs tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards them, and they as fairly quit him: yea <hi>God</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf alſo, for his Honour ſake, that he might ſtand clear in points of Juſtice concerning his dealing with his Vinyard, ſo with his people, ſaith, Judge oh ye Jews, or all, or any that doth, or ſhall hear and know of my dealing with it, and you, what more could I have done, &amp;c. and what leſs could it do to me in point of retaliation? and yet it hath affronted me with wilde grapes for tame, &amp;c. Alſo judge oh Houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> twixt my ways and yours, I appeal to you, ſo clear is my caſe, that I dare adventure to make the judg'd (yea my enemies) my Judges, &amp;c. thus let Governours nobly ſatisfie the ſcruples of the People, &amp;c. but ſee at the end of the Book this more perfect.</p>
            <p n="90">90. But lets ſuppoſe that the Parliament have not ſetled Cuſtome, Exciſe, nor Taxes, though I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive they did all, ſo alſo Convoy and Algier mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, &amp;c. by Acts, Orders, or Ordinances, &amp;c. and yet all is ſaid not no to be ſufficient for ſome ſudden and extraordinary Publike occaſions and exigents,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:151178:26"/>
&amp;c. What's then to be done? The univerſal Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Governour urgeth his want; its reply'd, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be by reaſon of other, and the ſaid great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes, &amp;c. ſo its a pretenſe: next, you ſay, is the higheſt Governour Judge alone? For anſwer to both which, I ſend you to Sect. 83. Alſo its urged, that its againſt <hi>Magna Charta;</hi> ſee therefore Sect. 106. to 111.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, you ſay, that a <hi>Parliament</hi> muſt be call'd, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>To this I will now anſwer you; lets ſuppoſe the caſe is ſudden and deſperate, &amp;c. as that the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> is now in the <hi>Downs</hi> with a mighty Navy, and our Sea-Forces unready, or abroad, &amp;c. And the Scots King hath a great Army with him, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that all the Factions in <hi>Scotland, England,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> do or will Arm it paſt diſarming, if not ſeen to in ſeaſon, &amp;c. and Treaſure is pretended to be wanting, and all are ſo divided, they know not which ſide to appear on &amp;c. Would you now diſpute about Laws allowance, and ceremonial ways of proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſo about Parliaments, when diſpatching is moſt neceſſary to prevent our <hi>Diſpatching;</hi> who on this ſudden and deſperate accident is Judge, ſay ye? who will you apply to, ſay I, to take a courſe to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them, but to him who hath the univerſal Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in his hand, though he were an Uſurper, yet no deſtroyer? For who elſe can, or who elſe dare (he being in Beeing) aſſume the Power? What courſe will you take on ſuch exigents, or on ſome hardſhips or ill uſage? Keeping to our Cautions, that is, to take heed of endangering the Nation to ruine by op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite Arms, &amp;c. Can you take a better courſe then
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:151178:27"/>
the concluſion of the Book will afford you; or as we do with Arbytrators, Phyſicians, Chyrurgians and Lawyers, on like exigents; whom wee can onely with good language, move to be faithfull to their truſt, alſo juſt and humane, and ſo to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their honours and reputations, and then adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture their killing and undoing of us.</p>
            <p>I have ſuppoſed as afore, on purpoſe to ſee if on any occaſions, or exigents, you will allow the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor &amp; his wiſe-counſel without a Law, yea againſt it, ſo without a <hi>Parliament,</hi> when it cannot be timely call'd to be Judges, or take a courſe to ſave you, and us all, as they can; if ye ſay no, then wee may bee loſt by diviſions and forreign oppoſitions; if ye an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer yea, then ye grant as much as I deſire; that is, exigents and neceſſities may be, or may be preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, though you and I diſcern them not, and that the Governours muſt be truſted, and ſo muſt, yea ought, without Law or Parliaments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſave the people as they can, &amp; for his pretending right or wrong, I have, and do ſend you to <hi>Sect.</hi> 124. and if ye have a better, a wiſer way on pretences, ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals or exigents, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhew it, and we comply, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="91">91. The intention of Laws, is to ſave us, and do us good, if the <hi>letter</hi> and intention claſh, which will you cleave too; for to <hi>contraries</hi> you cannot, and to <hi>deſtructives</hi> you ought not, make the <hi>Laws</hi> then, Oh ye Lawyers, more wiſely and in plain terms, that admit not of ſuch doubtfull and betraying con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, that ſo we may not be befool'd, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd by them, nor you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 94. If thus as afore, ſay you, why then was the King call'd to accompt? why ſuffer'd he, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for he had his pretences, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:151178:27"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Truly, if we had not had a viſible, autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and powerfull <hi>power</hi> to deal with him, wee ought to have ſuffered according to our poſition, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then indanger our Country to ruine, but the whole Nation, who ſent up the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and were bound in <hi>Honour, Honeſty,</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> to ſecond them, and were ſatisfied about ſeconding them, came up by hundreds and thouſands, &amp;c. offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to live and die with them. So that to my ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we made it hazardable and doubtfull, by dally<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him; for I conceive he might eaſily have been ſurprized long afore, but wiſe and juſt policies might prolong it for uſefull ends ſake. So I may be deceived, therefore will not deceive, ſo I judge not.</p>
            <p n="95">95. But as there was a viſible, likely, and an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſed able <hi>power</hi> as afore, in likeli-hood to carry it, without ſuch indangering to ruine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo there was cauſes proportionable for ſuch procedure, as ye may find in the L. Chief Juſtice <hi>Cook's</hi> Kings caſe. But what likely and juſt pretence could the <hi>King</hi> have to want, and ſo raiſe treaſure, by ſhip mony, Privy ſeals, Pole-mony, and what not, hee was at Peace with all neighbour Nations, Princes, and States. So alſo within himſelf, ſo was not inforced to keep three <hi>Armies,</hi> ſo long on foot to keep three <hi>Nations</hi> from <hi>Armies;</hi> alſo to oppoſe <hi>Forrainers,</hi> nor to have ſuch forces at <hi>Sea,</hi> to oppoſe our many enemies that would have ſeiz'd on us, he was no way exigented ſo might take his courſe by <hi>Parliament,</hi> but have not we been ſurpriſed by the <hi>Hollander,</hi> and exceedingly exigented as unprovided? moſt of our forces being abroad, or unready, and a long time the contention
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:151178:28"/>
held, to the expenſe of much treaſure; neither <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert,</hi> nor the <hi>French,</hi> nor the <hi>Breſt men of War</hi> medled with him; imploy'd he ſo many brave Fleets abroad, and that for uſeful, honourable, and humane ends and uſes, as in mating the unmatchable<note place="margin">The Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lander &amp; Turk.</note>, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming of many poor be-ſlaved ſouls, did For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Ambaſſadors throng in upon him as on us? who for the honour of our <hi>Country</hi> and our <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> thereof, muſt be anſwerably entertain'd, and ſo muſt thoſe ſent abroad, accordingly: And muſt not his Highneſs of force, though ſelf-ly humble, keep ſuch a ſtate and port, as may keep up the <hi>honour</hi> of ſuch a <hi>State</hi> or <hi>People,</hi> alſo his own <hi>State</hi> anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, as the <hi>Preſenter</hi> of ſuch a <hi>People,</hi> ſo that nothing may render us deſpicable, but rather double reſpect, as was the <hi>Sheba</hi> Queens about <hi>Solomon;</hi> and though <hi>Solomon</hi> counted all things vain, it was but reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, for he knew alſo there were other reſpects that rendred them uſeful; His <hi>Fame,</hi> as vain as it was by this accompt, yet made him famous, and did much conduce to him in points of fear, love, aw, reverence, and revenues, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="96">96. And what if our Countries, our Nations, &amp;c. were called the <hi>Houſe of the North,</hi> or <hi>Nore,</hi> or of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> as Spains is in a Bravery and Glory, only to out-brave, the <hi>Houſe of Austria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="97">97. But if you be not yet ſatisfied about your Higheſt Power and Governour, his juſt Power and Place, as neceſſitated, though I conceive I have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently aſſerted my <hi>Aſsertion.</hi> What ſay you to this of <hi>Moſes</hi> following? Sure, you dare not que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion his Right of Governing and Judging, ſeeing God in the Scriptures appears for him, and againſt
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:151178:28"/>
his oppoſers; ſo dare you not charge him as an Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: But if you dare not, I dare; and yet am I not inſolent; for I can diſcharge him when I pleaſe. I ſay then, that according to the received Tenents of Uſurpation, he was an Uſurper; but according to our definition or right Acceptation, at Sect. 47, 48. &amp;c. he was none, but very Authentick and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
            <p>Who is't proves <hi>Moſes</hi> choſen Governour by the univerſal free choice of the People? If not, What was he then by your ſayings? But ours quits him, and ſo renders him a true and right Governour, and a Righteous one alſo.</p>
            <p n="98">98. But you will ſay, he was choſen, and call'd, or ſent of God, ſo no <hi>Uſurper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What's this to man, as to them who know it not? They had only <hi>Moſes</hi> word, in his own behalf for it, except they would accept of him for his Miracles ſake, which yet they car'd not for, as of God: For can you ſay that they entertain'd him 'cauſe of God? Surely no, they were not ſo <hi>Godly:</hi> For why then excluded they <hi>Samuel</hi> whom they knew was of God? Why outed they God himſelf in <hi>Samuel? Samuel,</hi> this ſtubborn, this rebellious, this ſtiff-neckt people, have de-thron'd, uncrown'd, and diſ-ſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter'd me as well as thee: Sure, they that care not for God himſelf, care not for any ſent from him; ſo it appears they entertain'd <hi>Moſes</hi> only as a moſt hopeful Deliverer, and upon no other grounds, he giving good evidences thereof, by his wiſdom, care, carriage, faithfulneſs, and miracles, &amp;c. and the ſame grounds kept him in Government, for they knew not how to better themſelves. So we ſay,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:151178:29"/>
that <hi>Moſes</hi> was truly, juſtly, and authentically choſen and impowered, according to our Tenents; ſo that none of their choiceſt, or beſt choſen Kings or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, were more lawful Powers then was the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choſen <hi>Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="99">99. But we will begin with <hi>Moſes ab origine,</hi> that we may the better ſee the true ſtate of things, for our uſe. Its neceſſary then to take knowledge that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> liv'd together in <hi>Goſhen,</hi> where <hi>Joſeph</hi> plac'd them, and not mixtly or ſcatteringly amongſt the <hi>Egyptians;</hi> ſo they had their own Religion, Laws, and Government, Civil, and Eccleſiaſtical, which they enjoy'd about four hundred years till <hi>Moſes</hi> time; their Laws muſt needs be their <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> their Rights, Dues, and Priviledges, <hi>viz.</hi> to preſerve them in ſafety amongſt themſelves, ſo in their Rights of all ſorts, and to relieve them from wrong, &amp;c. Theſe, none but impowered Powers by choice and conſent, might juſtly invade or evade, by adding to, altering, or taking from, except with our cautions, which it may be they were not capable of; as are not many of our Pleaders for <hi>Magna,</hi> who are oft too <hi>poſitive</hi> and <hi>abſolute,</hi> and ſo indanger, or deſtroy all.</p>
            <p>But when the Monarch <hi>Moſes</hi> comes, he ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heaves the Door off the hinges, and turns the Houſe out at the Windows, and like an impetuous Torrent, bears down their Laws, their <hi>Magna Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> and all things afore him; and yet he doth no ſuch thing, but bears up all: In their poſitive and l<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>teral ſtrictneſs he bears them down, elſe they might upon ſome emergencies or exigents, bear him and his people down; but in their fair and well condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:151178:29"/>
conducing Intentionals for the Publike good, he bears all up: So, what he in their poſitive acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation ſuppreſſeth, to avoid ſuppreſſion, he advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth by wiſe <hi>Reſpectives,</hi> and ſo puts down <hi>Solomon</hi> the Wiſe<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> was wiſe, <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> witty.</note>, with the Wiſe. For according to juſt neceſſities, he invades, and evades Law, and ſo adds, alters, and abrogates, &amp;c. and yet neither Uſurpers nor Arbytraters it, as we have or will ſhew; for, all being perform'd, according to our Principles and premiſſes, he alters not their <hi>Magna</hi> in its intentions, but only in its dimenſions, as contracting or enlarg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it as it beſt conduc'd, and ſo bends and inclines it to juſt neceſſities inclinations; and in ſo doing, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifi'd it and himſelf: Thus, as ſome of their privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges by reaſon of their weakneſſes or wilfulneſſes in their journey, might prove offenſive to them, he contracts, them &amp; ſo enlargeth their liberties and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges in binding them; for, its a freedom, a privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to be bound, when (if at liberty) we would miſchief our ſelves; thus, our Chyrurgions to free us, binde us, and our Phyſitians do almoſt kill us, to keep us alive, and make us live: So, their right Priviledges would have wrong'd them, and it was ſome neceſſitated wrong'd doings (enforc'd by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) righted them at that time, &amp; in that condition.</p>
            <p>Circumciſion it ſelf, their moſt eſſential privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and the flower of their Crown, or <hi>Charta,</hi> &amp;c. was circumcis'd; and though in its nature ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly moſt unſeemly, ſavage, and ſevere; yet as it was enjoy'd and enjoyn'd, it was their only badge, mark, or character to diſtinguiſh them from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens and Pagans, and ſo render them refin'd, as the People of God, ſo that a curſe went on the uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcis'd,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:151178:30"/>
and now it was a curſe to be circumcis'd, for, for their forty years journey its laid aſide, and ſo in that point they paſs ſo long for Pagans: Their Law for Theft is altered to four-fold ſatisfaction, or ſervitude; ſo they hang not, as do we, but reſerve their Delinquents for uſeful ſervice, private or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, yet to give the privated ſatisfaction, which done, they return to themſelves, and are their own men again. A moſt ſevere Law, or tryal for a ſuſpected Wife is added, but ſeeing I cannot reach the reaſon thereof (though reaſon there might be) I compreſs, &amp;c. and chuſe rather to think, then to expreſs my ſelf impertinently, or to my compreſſion.</p>
            <p>Theſe three are only inſtanced to make appear his ſelf, (yet not ſelf-iſh) alterations, additions, or abbro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, as wiſe reſpective conſiderations call for, but infinite more of all ſorts may be obſerv'd he did; for, as appears in <hi>Exodus, Leviticus, Numbers,</hi> and <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> he new modell'd their whole Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, both <hi>Civil, Eccleſiastical,</hi> and <hi>Military,</hi> yet for the Publike Good, Peace and Safety ſake, and not for any by-ends of his own.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">I put all on Moſes cauſe Moſes to the people is all in all.</note>Infinite, troubleſome, and chargeable ſacrifices did <hi>Moſes</hi> alſo inſtitute and put on them, beſides a world of other buſying performances to take up their giddy heads in their long journey, enough to make <hi>Loyalty</hi> turn <hi>Loyaliſt,</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> a <hi>Rebel;</hi> and yet theſe <hi>Rebels</hi> rebell'd not as yet.</p>
            <p>Their Civil Government he wholly alters, adds to, or abrogates, as appears by his four laſt books, for its ſaid, <hi>Moſes</hi> did or commanded this, and that, &amp;c. By their Religious or Eccleſiaſtical Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he doth the like; for he ſets them a ſeventh
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:151178:30"/>
day, with the other 3 commands, never articulately ſet or commanded afore; he alſo dictates to them the ſix laſt, which of themſelves are Dictators, and ſo ſet themſelves, but not their ceremonies; as <hi>Reaſon</hi> ſaith plainly, <hi>Thou ſhalt not steal,</hi> but it ſaith not ſo plainly, <hi>Thou ſhalt reſtore juſt four-fold,</hi> ſo its diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table what Retaliation is righteſt. The whole <hi>Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood</hi> were of his creating, and he maketh his brother <hi>Aaron</hi> a <hi>Prelate,</hi> or <hi>prime Prieſt;</hi> he robes, ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ornaments him from head to foot, with taking Types, Ceremonies, and Ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars<note place="margin">The Occults were laid up in the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum.</hi> where only the High Prieſt might enter.</note> to take the People; the leſſer, the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or ſubordinate <hi>Prieſts</hi> he alſo creates, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and leſſons them (as he did their <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi>) of their charge, and offices, &amp;c. and when he ſees his time, he diſrobes <hi>Aaron,</hi> and robes his ſon <hi>Eleazer</hi> in his place.</p>
            <p>The Military Diſcipline he alſo orders &amp; ſettles it in chief on his Diſciple and Servant <hi>Joſhua,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Painces, Nobles and Prieſts, ſo the Souldier and all ſorts, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey him.</note> and nothing is done without, or againſt his order, nor any thing left undone that he commands, or countermands. He puniſheth to the purpoſe the 3 Rebellious Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and all their company and complices, for their bold prate, as, What haſt thou to do with us thou Uſurper, we know thy Original, and whom thou art? Art thou any more then a poor caſt-away,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 16.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered by accident, as if to caſt us away under co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of ſaving us? Whence then theſe thy preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions? In ſhort, thou takeſt too much upon thee <hi>Moſes,</hi> What? wilt thou who the other day pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be our Deliverer only, now turn our Goaler, and binde us to thy ſeverities, ſome of them under the notion of Sacrifice? A fine piece of Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie!
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:151178:31"/>
What? wilt thou that waſt againſt King <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Kinging it, ſo his Oppreſſions, Cruelties, and Tyrannies, alſo againſt Monarchy and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, or ſuch Kingly Government, Wilt thou now Lord and Maſter, yea King it over us? for what Monarch or King ever did more, or ſo much as doth the Monarch <hi>Moſes?</hi> Are we thy ſlaves or vaſſals that thou handleſt us thus arbytrarily? for thou haſt raz'd out our Laws, our Priviledges, our <hi>Charta,</hi> &amp;c. and put what thou pleaſeſt in their places, and if ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken knowledge of, then thou puniſheſt, or deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt us at thy pleaſure; witneſs thy maſſacring of three thouſand of the Lords people at about,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.27.</note> beſide many other miſchiefs done to us, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Again, thou haſt under pretence of a Paradiſe, a Canaan, a heavenly Jeruſalem, &amp;c. brought us out of Canaan, as out of a Country that flows with Milk and Honey, to an Utopia that hath nothing in it of acceptables,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 16 13.14.</note> but only of name, fame, and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; for not Egypt now, but this thy Canaan is our Houſe of Bondage, from which would to God we were freed and delivered, &amp;c. make us not blind <hi>Moſes,</hi> cauſe we cannot ſee inviſibles, which thou only as a <hi>Magi</hi> mayſt &amp;c. if thou canſt: In ſhort, come thou down to us, if thou wilt, for we will not come up to thee, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But, ſeeing <hi>Moſes</hi> though he did thus ſelf-ly Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchize it, yet it was not ſelf-iſhly, but for the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like good, he ſtill varying as neceſſities and conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies varied;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>250<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptains a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them.</note> ſo though he might decline Law, yet he vagar'id not therefrom, nor governed arbytra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, &amp;c. It coſt theſe Rebels dear, as the ruine of themſelves and their whole Families, as an exempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:151178:31"/>
puniſhment to deter and awe others from the like attempt, and ſo was conducing to the ſaving of the whole Body, the Family, or Houſe of this People, by lopping off a limb thereof, which elſe by ſuch fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionings and rebellions might have been endanger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ruine.</p>
            <p>Nor did <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpare his brother <hi>Aaron,</hi> nor <hi>Miriam</hi> his ſiſter, but handled them ſeverely for their ſeverities to him; as in their daring to vie it out with him in right of Power, &amp;c. As, <hi>What? Hath the Lord ſpoke only by Moſes? Hath he not ſpoken by us alſo?</hi> See Numb. 12. ſo that <hi>Miriam</hi> was leprous'd as white as ſnow: a tincture that fairly ſet off her foul and black qualities; and the Prelate <hi>Aaron</hi> was put to the <hi>Penance</hi> of a <hi>Palinodia,</hi> or <hi>Peccavi.</hi> Alas, my Lord <hi>Moſes!</hi> I beſeech thee charge us not with this ſin, I know we have done fooliſhly. Here's a great deſcention of a <hi>Brother,</hi> and a <hi>Prelate,</hi> to a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ick Brother. Surely, the Prince, the Monarch, the Laick <hi>Moſes,</hi> was in Power, Place, and Nature, ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to the Prelate <hi>Aaron:</hi> But now the<note n="*" place="margin">Words of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</note> 
               <hi>Laicks</hi> are a<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.27.</note> 
               <hi>Lay</hi> people, and the <hi>Levites</hi> their Lords, till ſome <hi>Moſes</hi> be-meet with them.</p>
            <p>He alſo commanded his Prieſts, the Levites, by his Law Martial, without Tryal, to kill and butcher their Brethren, and they obey, and ſo kill'd three thouſand at a bout; and ever ſince, many of that <hi>Tribe</hi> have continued <hi>Butchers.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">In their cruelties to the people.</note>
            </p>
            <p>He inforc'd the People themſelves alſo to drink the duſt of their dirty <hi>Calves,</hi> though gilded; and of their gods, cauſe golden.</p>
            <p>Thus, he hath the whole <hi>Legiſlative</hi> Power in his hand, as appears by all afore. He alſo ſelf-ly judges
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:151178:32"/>
all ſorts a long ſeaſon, till on advice he made Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, who were accountable to him, &amp;c. yet in all theſe proceedings nothing for ſelf-ends, but only as neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitated, or convenienced for the common good; for if Kinghood,<note place="margin">Neer to a Queen as being a Kings daughter.</note> Prelacy, or pleaſures, or his own ends he had aim'd at in their delivery, ſure, his Queen-mother <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s daughter, and <hi>Egypt</hi> for her ſake, with his own wiſdom, learning, and policy, as a <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi,</hi> would have gone neer to have King'd him, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever to advance him as high, or higher, in all likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and that without any ſuch ſufferings, or danger of ruineing by ſo rude and boiſterous a people; how then is <hi>Moſes</hi> an Uſurper? How, Arbytrary in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment by the aforeſaids? Yet I have heard, that <hi>Machiavel</hi> makes him both, though he be neither. But what may not <hi>Much-evil</hi> do if we undo him not? which we will if we can.</p>
            <p>For ſhould the People have had the Government in their own hands, and only askt <hi>Moſes</hi> advice and counſel in point of their deliverance; or ſhould <hi>Moſes</hi> have taken any of them in by way of counſel and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, <hi>ſurely</hi> they had return'd to the houſe of Bondage again; however, never to <hi>Canaan;</hi> for by diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, diſputes, and contentions, oppoſitions, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts, they would have deſtroy'd themſelves in the way; ſo he was neceſſitated to Monarchize it, and ſelf-ly manage all, as without the People, or their Parliaments conſent, or councel; and yet he doth all things wel, wiſely and faithfully for their good. And this may be his Highneſs caſe at this time, why he dare not (as we are factiouſly divided, qualifi'd, and condition'd) make uſe of Parliaments or People, in points of advice and counſel, leſt conteſts and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:151178:32"/>
for ſelf ends, and priorities of parties and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to rule and carry it, delay or croſs all; and ſo his <hi>Highneſs</hi> is enforc'd to <hi>Moſes</hi> it all along.</p>
            <p n="100">100. By our times Tenent alſo, <hi>Joſhua</hi> was an <hi>Uſurper,</hi> for he was only of his Maſter <hi>Moſes</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king; nay, what will become of moſt of their Kings and Governours, <hi>Saul, David,</hi> and <hi>Jeroboam</hi> exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted, who were only authentick, according to recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Tenents, as choſen by the People, as well as of God? For <hi>Saul,</hi> ſee 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 9.2. For <hi>David,</hi> ſee 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.5. For <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> ſee 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12.3.20. <hi>Solomon</hi> was only created by his Father, the reſt cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated themſelves; for neither did any Law, or the People create them; <hi>Ergo,</hi> The People may (by our times poſitions and practiſe, as did the three Princes againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> afore, and ſome of our Clergy now againſt his <hi>Highneſs</hi>) rebel it, and ſo moſt uncivilly, malapertly, and audaciouſly, mouth, and clamour it againſt their Kings and Governours, to the incenſing of the People, and ſo to the endangering the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like; alſo not owning them for lawful Powers and Authorities, the Judges, nor any can acknowledge, or act under them, but might (for good examples ſake) had they Might, juſtly rebel againſt them, though to the ruine of all: A moſt judicious and Judge-like kind of reaſoning! Thus might moſt of their Kings and Governours have been ſerv'd. But our prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Safety of the People,</hi> is of another minde, and flies to our cautions, as to ſo many Cities of Refuge, from ſuch <hi>Sinons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, conſider further, what abuſes<note n="*" place="margin">Beſides their own perſonal vices.</note> ſome of the beſt of their Kings and Governours offered to the People, and yet our Principles and Cautions allow
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:151178:33"/>
no ruinous rebellion, but only to proceed as we have cautioned, or as at Sect. 124, And we condemn all ſuch actions, for all the greatneſs of the Actors, and ſay, they deſerve thereafter; and its only <hi>Salus</hi> ſafety that ſaves both them and us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saul</hi> maſſacred eighty and odd Prieſts at a bout, and ruin'd their City <hi>Nob,</hi> with all the innocents therein, both men, women, and children. <hi>David</hi> make drunk, and then murdered <hi>Uriah,</hi> and raviſh'd his Wife, and moſt unconſcionably gave half of his endeared brother <hi>Jonathans</hi> ſon <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> his land, to his ſervant, that Traytor <hi>Ziba;</hi> and yet there was (I take it) oaths, vows, and covenants be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Jonathan</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> to be faithful to each others ſeed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ahab</hi> moſt hypocritally (under pretenſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as zeal to the honour of God and his name) caus'd <hi>Naboth</hi> to be ſton'd as a Blaſphemer, and that done, ſtole his Vinyard alſo under the ſame <hi>vizor. Solomon</hi> alſo oppreſt the People ſo, one way or other, as it obſtacled his ſon <hi>Rehoboams</hi> Kinging. Yet the People wiſely conniv'd at all in <hi>Solomon,</hi> ſo in the reſt, rather then endanger the whole Publike by inciting clamours or rebellions, or any unſeemly, malapert, provoking carriage or language.</p>
            <p>The three aforeſaid degenerated Gentlemen or Princes,<note place="margin">What's a Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine in priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to theſe, ſo to <hi>Moſes</hi> proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingss?</note> 
               <hi>Saul, David,</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> in theſe, &amp; thoſe particulars, were yet good Kings and Governours to the General; Muſt the <hi>General</hi> ſuffer or be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered for Individual or Particular ſufferings? Surely no, it muſt not; yet keep to our Cautions, and take your courſe, elſe keep at diſtance.</p>
            <p>Said not <hi>David</hi> of <hi>Saul,</hi> though his enemy, yea,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:151178:33"/>
and the enemy alſo of God and man, as to the Prieſts aforeſaid, &amp;c. <hi>Weep and mourn O ye Daughters of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem! Weep and mourn for Saul, who cloth'd you with Scarlet, and fed you with</hi> (Nectar and Ambroſia) <hi>milk and honey, and deckt your ears with Pendants,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>and your Apparel with all kindes of pleaſing Beautifyings, and amorouſly trimm'd your Treſses;</hi> who alſo fought your Battels, and foyl'd your enemies, and loſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to ſave you.</p>
            <p>And for King <hi>David,</hi> a better, a more faithful, or valianter King or Governour, could not be to the Publike, then was he.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Solomon</hi> his ſon, though he oppreſt ſome parties of the People, in the Building of his Houſe at <hi>Millo,</hi> &amp;c. yet the generality had ſuch Peace and Plenty as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>John</hi>'s <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> promiſeth to her Citizens and Inhabitants; for ſilver and gold rival'd it in number and weight with the ſtones in the ſtreet, and in value with new <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> twelve gates, &amp;c. Muſt theſe be made away for thoſe? Muſt the Publike ſuffer for ſome Individual or parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ſufferings; Your judgements, you wiſe and juſt men.</p>
            <p>For the Peoples anſwering of <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> or his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to them, it was not an unauthoriſed, nor an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable party that perform'd it, but was like our Parliament in nature, ſo in their power and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings with and againſt the King, for it was the act of the whole Kingdom whom they preſented, and by whom they were authoriſed, who were in honour and honeſty bound to ſecond them, and they did ſo; <hi>Rehoboam</hi> alſo was not ſetled, nor as yet accepted of the people, who had thus reſerved themſelves, till
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:151178:34"/>
they had found out his reſerves; Heir to the Crown he was not, and nothing had he done by way of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and deſert of a Scepter, ſo he could not lay any juſt claim thereto, and ſo they juſtly diſclaim'd him, having a likely power to do it, without endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering their Country, and well he deſerv'd it, that would ſo malapertly tell a whole Nation to their Teeth (he having no right as afore to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but their good wils) how he would ſerve them: How could they do leſs having power, then deſert and diſpower him ſo? But had he been ſetled, received, and inveſted with the univerſal <hi>Militia,</hi> or power, ſo as it would have hazarded the Nations ruine; ſure, the people would (as did <hi>David</hi>) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nive at <hi>Joab,</hi> and ſay, <hi>The ſons of Zerviah are too hard for me,</hi> ſo is the King for us: So<note place="margin">He was but young in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, as not yet eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> 
               <hi>Saul</hi> as wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly held his peace, when ſome of the people ſcornful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid, <hi>How ſhall this man ſave us:</hi> alſo <hi>they brought him no preſents;</hi> Thus <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David</hi> kept to our cautions, elſe might they have been <hi>cauteriz'd,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And though the Prophets reproved ſome of their Kings and Governours, &amp;c. yet was it not in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, as on a Theater or Scaffold, <hi>viz.</hi> in their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Pulpits, which are confluenc'd with people, as is Cheapſide croſs, or the Exchange, and there mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertly, daringly, and contemptuouſly clamour, and exclaim, to an incenſing the people, and ſo to an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangering the publike; but they perform'd it only 'twixt the King and themſelves; or if in publike, yet reſpectively, in private, as not at their Exchange, ſo nor in ſuch inſulting and incenſing poſture and language, as afore.</p>
            <p>All their <hi>Uſurping Kings</hi> (if you'l have it ſo) which
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:151178:34"/>
were all but the afore Excepteds, took upon them <hi>Moſes</hi>-like almoſt, both in Civil, Eccleſiaſtical, and Military affairs; their <hi>Prieſts</hi> they made and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>made <hi>ad placitum;</hi> the like of their Warriours of all ſorts, as you may read of <hi>Saul, David,</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> and the reſt. <hi>Saul</hi> when he ſee any one fit for the War, took him to him, and yet no endangering re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion enſu'd thereon.</p>
            <p>Yea <hi>Joſhua, Moſes</hi> Miniſter or Servant, equall'd his Maſter in Soveraignty of command, though an <hi>Uſurper</hi> by this Times Tenents, as only inveſted by his Maſter <hi>Moſes;</hi> yet was he obey'd of all the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, Princes, and Peers, ſo of the Souldiery, Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and People of all ſorts, without endangering rebellion, or irreverent and uncivil clamours, geſts, or geſtures: Read his Book, and you ſhall find this Servant, this Uſurper (if an Uſurper youl have him, though we ſay otherwiſe, as having the Peoples Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities and Safety that choſe him, and authoris'd him rather then fail to aſſume, to uſurp and hold the Government, of, by, and from his Maſter <hi>Moſes</hi> only, he ruling for the Peoples good, welfare, and ſafety, and not for his own by ends of any nature, in oppoſition to theirs) did juſtly maſter it, and rule over his maſters, the People; yet ſervant like, for their ſervice, as afore.</p>
            <p>For, <hi>Joſhua</hi> ordered the <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> and <hi>Levites,</hi> ſo all things elſe, and that ſelf-ly; ſo that ſelf doings, if <hi>Well,</hi> are well enough; for, the main is <hi>well-doing, how,</hi> is ceremonial to <hi>well,</hi> or the thing it ſelf; Yet let <hi>Ceremonies</hi> be alſo obſerv'd if they may with ſafety and conveniency; if not, <hi>Circumciſe</hi> them.</p>
            <p>Its true, <hi>Joſhua</hi> came well fortifi'd and ſeconded
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:151178:35"/>
with Miracles and Wonders for his reception, equal in value and worth, though not in multitude to his Maſter <hi>Moſes,</hi> under whom he was brought up, as was his Maſter under the Egyptian <hi>Magies;</hi> and no doubt <hi>Moſes</hi> inſtructed him with wiſdom and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy how to govern the people when he was gone, as not daring to leave them to themſelves: But here wiſe <hi>Moſes</hi> fay'ld in not providing <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s but only a <hi>Joſhua,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Some abſolute certain way of ſafe Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> &amp;c. Let the ſiege of <hi>Ai,</hi> and <hi>Jericho,</hi> ſo his rivalling it with his maſter in dividing of <hi>Jordan</hi>'s Rivers, Red Sea-like, with other Miracles that his Story or Book yeilds; eſpecially his mating him, in fixing &amp; ſtation<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the remote, the immenſe, the unbounded and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtay'd Sun in his impetuous hurry, and ſwift career, on his own Theater or Stage, only with a God-like command, as, Sun ſtand thou ſtill, and ſtir not, &amp;c. Witneſs for him, that he mated as afore, not only his Maſter, but his Maſters<note place="margin">All the People.</note> alſo; yet by ſervant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to them all in his adminiſtrations and ſervices of all ſorts of humanities, for their good, their peace, and welfares, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">I am pos'd, ſo poſitive it not.</note>How puniſht he poor <hi>Achan</hi> for a theftleſs theft to ſee to? For could <hi>Achan</hi> ſteal where he might kill? Ah me! yet it kill'd <hi>Achan,</hi> and infinite Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents enough (did not our Principle forbid) to have rebell'd it, &amp;c. But a wiſe, a wary, a <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi>-like connivance and complyance on any ſide, (where the ſons of <hi>Zerviah</hi> are too hard) prohibit ſuch proceedings; yet the depraved of our Clergie, and wicked Laity, make a profeſſion of ſuch <hi>Prate,</hi> ſuch <hi>Practiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, What did any of their aforeſaid Kings or
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:151178:35"/>
Governours afore-hand, for their King-hoods. <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> excepted, who performed beyond exception, in their point of Redemption. Be ingenious then, oh you our <hi>Moſes,</hi> his adverſaries, and deny it if you can, hath he not <hi>Moſes</hi>-like, declin'd all Egyptian pleaſures, blandiſhments, and delights, beſides ſafety, eaſe, and reſt, and put himſelf on all ſorts of hardſhips, dangers, and ſufferings for his Brethrens ſake? Hath not his limbs, life and liberty been engaged to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingage us? Came he not ſeconded and fortifi'd with Miracles (for this our time) when miracles are mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, as out of date: Thus our <hi>Moſes</hi> mated <hi>Moſes,</hi> reſpectively in miracles, though not in multitude, nor poſitively; I am ſure I have heard, This, That, and the Other Victory, hath been acknowledged mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous, and of a <hi>Divine</hi> Dye, or the hand of God or a Deity ſeconding man; take it which way you pleaſe, its miraculous; either for man himſelf to act ſo, or for God to ſecond a man ſo.</p>
            <p>Now if <hi>Moſes</hi> deliver his people with ſuch hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips and ſufferings each way, will you not allow him to preſerve himſelf and them when he hath done? Which he cannot do, but hazard both, if he ſhould deliver the Power out of his hand into theirs? For how knows he how it will be handled? He knows his own Power and Faithfulneſs, an others he could not know; But he knew well enough none was capable to that degree, therefore he is neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to hold the Government from the whole Nation and all their Governours, till he had tutor'd his ſervant <hi>Joſhua</hi> for that purpoſe, he alſo held it for their ends, not his own, except in part for his ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, with theirs; and it was a juſt and wiſe aſſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:151178:36"/>
and retention, all things conſidered. If you will ſay each one may pretend ſo. I anſwer, which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer may ſerve for all ſuch allegations and ſayings, as for this, they may ſo pretend, and abuſe with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſes, which I neither allow of, nor can help; but the Poſition as I have poſtured it, is in ſelf right, though ſome do abuſe with it.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Moſes</hi> was truly and juſtly their Lord<note place="margin">As their Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</note> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector at leaſt, yea their King in nature, and point of Power, though not of grace; as wanting the beauty and glory of the Name King, and ſome other ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonials and perquiſites, neceſſary to opinion, but not to judgement; which ſaith, that its Natures, and not Names; its occults, and not occulars, entitle to the title King, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But ſome trecherous and politique pretending Cavaliers or Malignants, would have <hi>Moſes</hi> reſigne up his <hi>Militia,</hi> his <hi>Abiſhag,</hi> or <hi>Miſtris,</hi> to <hi>Adonijah;</hi> for it was only a Truſt till delivered out of <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s hand; as for future, they were reſolv'd to protect themſelves, or chuſe their Protector. But wiſe and wary <hi>Moſes</hi> did ſee, that this was but to diſ-arm him, and then arm themſelves againſt him; for when done, he was undone: For that now, Royaliſts and all ſorts of Malignants, like the three ſeditious Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, with their complices &amp; companions, would have call'd him to accompt for executing their King <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> in the Red Sea, and ſo un-kinging them for fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, others would have had a bout with him for changing their Laws, and invading their <hi>Magna,</hi> &amp;c. ſo for uſurping the Government, though all for the beſt, &amp;c. Others for tampering with their Religion, and bringing in a world of Novelties, and ſo crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:151178:36"/>
of Sects. &amp;c. as they may pleaſe to notion them; and all ſorts, for his inticing them out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> their <hi>Canaan,</hi> by his blandiſhments and flatteries of an <hi>Utopian Canaan;</hi> for to them the Wilderneſs (which was but the way to <hi>Canaan</hi>) paſt for <hi>Canaan</hi> it ſelf as being out of hopes and expectation, by reaſon of their long, their tedious, and wearyſome jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, of ever meeting with any other, being alſo tir'd with ſufferings by the way, amongſt the reſt, the loſs of their Egyptian Fleſh-pots, and choice ſallads of all ſorts, troubled them; ſo it was much better with them when they were under King <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> or ſerv'd the Queen of Heaven, though in Hell, and ſacrific'd to her, then now, as they are under their new ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer, their earthly Monarch <hi>Moſes,</hi> whoſe Heaven to them is Hell.</p>
            <p>So let <hi>Moſes</hi> his intentions and endeavours be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo fair and good, yet if accidentals croſs, he is croſt; for like weaklings, they judge by accidental iſſues, and not by ingenious grounds, ends, intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and apparent endeavours, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Their oft murmuring againſt him, as we have in part inſtanced, makes good theſe to be their intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on him, could they with pretenſes and arguments have argued him out of his Armor, or to lay aſide his lance: But wiſe and wary <hi>Moſes,</hi> though Dove-like meek and milde he was, and no Serpent, yet had a Serpent, and was himſelf Serpentine, ſo would not be outed by arguments, nor untruſs, to be truſs'd up, therefore held his power, for his own, and their good and ſafety, and ſo improv'd it, and abus'd it not for ſelf ends.</p>
            <p>Now whether the aforeſaids ſuit with his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:151178:37"/>
Actions, Doings, and Endeavours, and his Uſage by our ſeditious <hi>Korahs, Dathans,</hi> and <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rams,</hi> in their exclamations, cenſures, and trecheries againſt Him, 'cauſe of ſome croſſing accidents and ſufferings in our way to <hi>Canaan,</hi> ſo in their intentions on his rendition of his power, as only a Truſt, for that now they would truſt to themſelves, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the intentions of thoſe pretenſions, reach not to call him to an account for all? As ſhould <hi>Moſes,</hi> had he been ſo mopiſh, I appeal; and ſo do I, whether they be not very good reaſons in his Highneſs, as in <hi>Moſes,</hi> to retain the Power, had we no other reaſons for his ſo doing, but them. But I add alſo, that for his keeping the Power and Government with our cautions, I ſee not but that God and his Highneſs are incorporated therein (as I think I may make bold to ſay God and <hi>Samuel</hi> were) ſo that to clamour, except, or clandeſtine it, or to incenſe the people to faction or party it againſt him, and ſo againſt their Country and themſelves, its like thoſe three ſeditious Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men or Princes againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> and ſo againſt God: ſo now againſt our <hi>Moſes,</hi> as we have caution'd it, is againſt God; for we have prov'd him of God, and ſo of Divine Ordination, in his relation of right to the Government; ſo that out one, out both, in that point: And what are thoſe that will out both God and man! But &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now lets ſuppoſe that any King or Governour over us, ſhould (which God forbid) <hi>Solomon</hi>-like; infinite it in Wives and Concubines, or like <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, or King <hi>David,</hi> abuſe their Subjects wives, and murder their husbands, or <hi>Saul</hi>-like, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der eighty and odd Prieſts at a bout, yet none of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:151178:37"/>
theſe particulars juſtifie a rebellion to endanger our ruine, nor to uncivil, rude, booriſh, and clowniſh clamors, or impudent darings, but only to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend, peaceable and quiet information; for what Prince, or Governour, or men of Power and Place, can bear ſuch inſolent dares and threatnings to their diſgrace, whereas men of the meaneſt rank, though faulty, cannot endure publikly to be made <hi>Publicans,</hi> let each one examine himſelf, and he will find it an infinite diſhonour to bear with ſuch Malapertneſs, as if <hi>aw'd,</hi> which renders ſuch Powers contemptible, and invites rather to a ſtiffneſs to oppoſe, then to hearken to by way of remedy; nor have we to do with any in ſuch a way, though we ſee (as in the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Princes,) ſuch and ſuch vices and failings in ſome particulars, ſo long as they are in the general good Governours to the People, for they are but men in parts, though gods in place and power; and they muſt have their grains of weight, as muſt mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er men, as they have greater Tryals and Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>I will yet ſuppoſe higher, admit an honeſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, Pagan, or Atheiſt (if you will have it ſo) were in Government, and diſſembles a Religion and Zeal, the better to pleaſe, rule, and govern, &amp;c. and he doth govern well and juſtly, and gives thee thy conſcience, with our cautions againſt unconſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles under colour thereof, what's this to thee that he is a Pagan, an Infidel as thou call'ſt him; to God it is, and to none elſe. One hath thrown down <hi>Baal</hi>'s Altar, what's this to the <hi>Bawlers?</hi> who under pretence for <hi>Baal,</hi> have their own baſe ends; for its <hi>Baal</hi> is only concern'd, who if he be offended, knows
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:151178:38"/>
how to right himſelf. See then thou perform the duty of thy place, as at our application Sect. 124. alſo pray for him or them, likewiſe endeavour by thy good counſel, ſo thy precepts and practiſe, to ſettle in each one, love, obedience, and peaceable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs towards him, for his humanities, goodneſs, and protection of thee, thine, and all ſorts, as thy Native Country, &amp;c. and for the care, pains, and hazards he undergoes for thee, and us all.</p>
            <p n="101">101. <hi>Object.</hi> But it may be ſaid, to what end theſe ſtories of <hi>Moſes, Joſhua, Judges</hi> or <hi>Kings,</hi> &amp;c. What are they to us? we have our own Laws and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſetled, &amp;c. and ſuch and ſuch priviledges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed on, as they had not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, they are to us, and you have already ſeen it, could you conceive, or remember what ye have ſeen, and you ſhall ſee it to the full, if you can fully ſee.</p>
            <p>We have proved 1. That neither <hi>Moſes,</hi> nor <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua</hi> were Uſurpers, though not vocally choſen by the people, 'cauſe yet better choſen, <hi>viz.</hi> by ſome of our principles, as by the Peoples neceſſities; next, as taking and accepting, or aſſuming the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not for their own by, baſe, or unjuſt ends, but as neceſſitated for the Peoples good, &amp; ſo improving their proceedings; and who doth as did they, are no Uſurpers, nor Arbytrarie Governours, &amp;c. Unjuſt Uſurpation is to invade the Government, without ſo many of our grounds at Sect. 43. to 53. ſo 78. to 83. as will juſtifie the aſſumption and retention.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Admit Uſurpers they, or any of the Kings were, yet governing well, or though ſomwhat amiſs, yet not deſtructively; no attempts are to be made
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:151178:38"/>
againſt them, to the endangering of the Publike, but application only, as at Sect. 124. For though <hi>Moſes</hi> was taken for an Uſurper by the three Princes and the Peoples murmurings and undertakings againſt him, you ſee how they were puniſht for it, and that juſtly, conſidering he improv'd his beſt endeavours for the Publike good, nor were his neer relates, <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Miriam</hi> favoured, but upon their ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Though as faulty as the aforeſaid Princes, yea as <hi>Jeroboam;</hi> yet we ſay as next afore, that only ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, reverend, and peaceable Language and Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations are to be made, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That on exigents and juſt neceſſities for the general good, as did <hi>Moſes,</hi> when he durſt not truſt, nor uſe the peoples counſel in their delivery, or paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to <hi>Canaan,</hi> by reaſon of our Reaſons afore, he was forc'd to Monarchize it, and ſo ſelf-ly to order and manage all; and had he not ſo done, they had been undone. The like may other Governours on enforcing exigents do.</p>
            <p>I grant ſuch proceedings as at 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> to be amiſs, were the People capable; if not, they are juſt and right as I have order'd and caution'd them, elſe not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note, what follows, is ſpoken as it relates to the Publike.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I will give you my judgement at large what's Arbytrarie Power; for I believe my betters every way are as bad as my ſelf, if not worſe, as, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken in it; and ſo ſhall we be in all things, if we call things ſo and ſo, and ſo let them go without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther purſuit or proſecution of them, by diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and diſtributing, ſo by defining or bounding, &amp;c.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:151178:39"/>
likewiſe if we indefinite it, when we ſhould demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, and univerſalize it Rethorically for Logical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſo infer as from the laſt, and ſo are oft too late.</p>
            <p>Arbytrarie power (you will ſay) is to rule by Will and not by Law; but I ſay, this is not right, 'cauſe not rightly bounded and cautioned; for, you infer, that what's not of Law, is of Luſt and Will in the worſt ſence, and it may ſo be, and yet alſo it may not be ſo; ſo whilſt you neither define nor diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh aright, you confound and deſtroy all.</p>
            <p>By your definition of Arbytrarie Power, as afore, <hi>Moſes</hi> is condemn'd, who is juſtifi'd both of God and man, as you have heard; ſo alſo you condemn al pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings that are not according to Law, as if of luſt and Will, in your ſenſe, which is not ſo; for, if of a will rightly rectifi'd, and juſtly neceſſitated too, call it as you will, though a will it be, as not <hi>Legal</hi> Law, yet its in it ſelf or nature a Law, that binds againſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangering or deſtructive Laws ſelf-ly ſo, or made ſo by accidents or exigents, or by the peoples pravities or weakneſſes.</p>
            <p>I ſay then, that to rule by Law (when lawleſs) is cunningly to rule arbytrarily, as by Luſt and Will, and colour it with Law, againſt the very end of Law and Governours; and to rule by Will as we have caution'd it, is to rule by Law, though againſt Law, for its a lawful Will, as agreeing with Laws end and intention (though it fall out with its letter) which is for conducings to publike peace and ſafety.</p>
            <p>If you ſhall ſtill ſay, that this invaſion, or that evaſion or abrogation of Law muſt be with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples conſent in a Parliament, I ſay ſo too, if it may
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:151178:39"/>
be ſo, provided rightly compos'd and conſtituted; if not, not; but as we have ſaid afore.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſay then <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ummarily as foll<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>weth, That</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arbytrarie Power</hi> is to rule by, or to keep to Law, or Laws letter, when they prove endangering, &amp;c. or not ſo complying to the Publike as others, except you would that the Publike ſhould be endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered, or deſtroyed, or not better benefited.</p>
            <p>Next, <hi>Arbytrarie Power</hi> is, to break, or not uſe publike benefiting Laws for the Publike or particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars their accomodations, but only for partial or ſelf ends ſake.</p>
            <p>Aga<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, Its alſo to alter good Laws for worſe, or not to accomodate with better if it may be.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Its ſelf-ly to alter good or bad Laws for better, without giving the people their due and right of honour and conſent by way of a Parliament, if They and the Time be capable thereof; if not, not; but this is a fair condition failing, if a failing.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/> Again, Law is ſelf-ly abſolute, and therefore as occaſion oft are or may be, its very injurious, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, and deſtructive.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> Reaſon is reſpective, and ſo wiſely varies from Law according to juſt occaſions, and neceſſities for Publike good, and ſo avoids what it can, ſuch ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings and enclines to all conducings.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="C"/> To rule by Law then, if it prove as at <hi>A.</hi> is for ought I know, to rule like a Mad-man, or a wicked and wily Machiavel; as under pretenſe of zeal to Law, to act lawleſſes, as things dangerous to the Publike: This is to rule by Will, and Luſt, and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly colour it with Law, and ſo is arbytrary power though Legal.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:151178:40"/>Will therefore, and Arbytrarie Power (as you cal it, yet) if qualifi'd as at <hi>B.</hi> is the only wiſe, juſt, ſafe and lawful (though not legal) ruling and governing. <hi>See then to wiſe qualifications, and let fooliſh articula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and quarrellings go.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Poſition in it ſelf is right, though any one under any colour or pretence ſhould do wrong by it,<note place="margin">Wrong grounds.</note> either in degree or <hi>Pedigree.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Clamour no more then hence-forward, that this, or that is without, againſt, or contrary to Law, and therefore Arbytrarie, if our <hi>Poſition</hi> at <hi>B.</hi> bear it out, ſeeing it hath reaſon, wiſdom, and the publike good, and juſt neceſſities on its ſide, and only igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and folly againſt it.</p>
            <p>And except ſo qualifi'd, we allow no deviation from Law but will that each Individual (but not the publike) ſuffer; and attend its alteration by wiſe <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Law</hi> hath held us too long from the Lord and Judge of the Law, to whom we now return to perform the remain of our Duty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We ſay then, That</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="102">102. The higheſt Univerſal Judge, may, as I have in part ſaid afore, ſelf-ly judge all, but yet accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Laws in being, 'cauſe they are each ones rule and guide, elſe they might be ſurpriz'd and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd, &amp;c. But he being the higheſt Judge, is a Chancelor alſo; and as he may create a Chancery, ſo may he ſelf-ly Chancelor it, and check the ridged letter of the Law for its intention, which the ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate and ſubſtitute Judges cannot do without ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to him, or licenſe from him, from hence grows pardons, as the offence and offender may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:151178:40"/>
thereof, which ask many conſiderations, why one for the ſame fact may be juſtly pardoned, and not another; as this for one of them, as that he hath been very faithful and ſerviceable, yea a deliverer of his Country, or as his life may exceedingly conduce thereto, and our Country would ſuffer much to loſe him; but the Truth is, here are more conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be had, then I can now conſider of.</p>
            <p n="103">103. So all publike Offices that relate to him, he muſt ſelf-ly perform, or ſee perform'd, and he ought alſo to call them to account about their faithful diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of them to the people, or to him for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, alſo to hear the people if he can, in their appeals, and puniſh their abuſers, &amp;c. and this is <hi>Moſes,</hi> yea King-like. King <hi>David</hi> deſcended to hear the tatling <hi>Tekoite;</hi> and his ſon <hi>Solomon</hi> the two Huzzies, the <hi>Harlots.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely the Judges in difficulties of Law, may not ſelf-ly reſolve it, but as <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Judges, who it may be might ſome of them, and in ſome points, be as, or more able then <hi>Moſes,</hi> yet, as it was dubious, and ſo too hard for them, <hi>Moſes</hi> (as <hi>Joab</hi> to <hi>David</hi>) muſt have the honour of it, by acknowledging it his right of place, ſo as if of ability, though ſomtimes not ſo able, ſo that he with them, or any other of his wiſe Counſellors, may, reſolve it, though <hi>Moſes</hi> ſelf-ly reſolv'd all.</p>
            <p n="104">104. Certainly, it concerns the higheſt Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, who is Judge of all, and ſhould (could it be) judge all, it concerns him, I conceive, to be an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute rationaliſt, for that reaſon is the intention of Law, and the Goſpel alſo, though ſome Lawyers and Goſpellers oft reach it not; but being ſo, where
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:151178:41"/>
Law fails, or is dark, obſcure, or ridged, yet right reaſon will reach it, and if he be not ſtrongly ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, the Lawyers, but eſpecially the Goſpellers, will be too hard for him, and ever and anon ſurprize him: one, with, this is Law, that, not; alſo, ere is no Law for this, and here is Law againſt that &amp;c. and thoſe of the depraved Clergy will with their wyles, Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſicks, and Supernaturals beguil us, and out <hi>Phu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,</hi> Nature, and Reaſon, and grace alſo; but they ought not, nor ſhall, &amp;c for we ſhall (I hope) finde <hi>Commenſurators</hi> for all, let them commence as high as they can.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But</hi> Magna Charta <hi>is pleaded in behalf of our Priviledges, ſo Law alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="106">106. This <hi>Magna</hi> &amp;c. I never read, but now I will read ſomthing of it, yet by imagination only, and when done, anſwer them, and by that, anſwer all as are ſo condition'd, the reſt will anſwer for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Magna Charta</hi> is Law, and Law is in part al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready reſolv'd, and here the reſt ſhall. Suppoſe then as followeth.</p>
            <p n="107">107. That the People did well and wiſely make ſure work for the priviledge of calling their Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments once in two years, and to ſit till ſuch or ſuch a time, and this they claim ſtill, &amp; except, as wrong'd, and a great piece of injuſtice, and breach of truſt in the Governour, not to make good the ſame.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, Are we in the condition we were? will our preſent condition allow thereof? If we were as we were, it were claimable, but not as we are. The King, Peers, Prelats, and Prieſts of all ſorts, had their places in Parliament, or priviledges to their
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:151178:41"/>
minde, and ſo had Lawyers alſo; ſo when Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were call'd, they need not faction it for their places, being already plac't, and that in great pomp, power and command, and queſtion'd not their ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, they were ſo ſecure, till at laſt <hi>Elihu</hi>'s little dark cloud appear'd, whoſe expanſion and extenſion, they foreſee, would cloud their whole Heaven of glory, and render it dark and deſpicable: But now every Parliament is packt and compos'd on purpoſe, of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral parties, for the reſtauration of the aforeſaids: Alſo the Prieſts of all ſorts ſect it, ſo do all religious perſons faction and party it; yea, the ſeveral Churches claſh: ſo that the diſtinct Bodies of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and People, make one Body of <hi>Diſſentanies</hi> or things divers, and ſome of abſolute contraries: ſo that what by the weakneſs of ſome, and the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs and wilfulneſs of otherſome, and the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of moſt, time is loſt in confounding conteſts: Alſo Religion's rigidneſs and <hi>Meandrian</hi> intricacies are too hard for moſt of them, ſo for all ſorts, and doth more confound and trouble, then doth <hi>confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <p>The infinity of Sects and Opinions makes good what I ſay, which to diſſolve, is more then an <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culean</hi> labour, and asks time, till the diſſolution of <hi>Time</hi> to end it.</p>
            <p>A wiſe Governour ſeeing this, and that the time preſent is not as that paſt; ſo that the aforeſaid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations will not allow the calling of a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by reaſon of over-powering factions, to the endangering the peace and ſafety of the People, which his place, truſt, charge enjoyns him to prevent, ſo he cannot give way thereto, elſe would; for its
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:151178:42"/>
not now a liberty, but a bondage, and ſo is contrary to his end of a faithful Governour; and would you have him faithleſs, and act contrary to his end, as to endanger? &amp;c. I hope no.</p>
            <p n="108">108. For the aforeſaid reaſons, as by you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd, he is forc't to ſupply Parliaments by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and by a wiſe and faithful Councel, ſo by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations, Orders and Ordinances, yet all in a ſafe way, alſo ready, quick and ſhort, without loſs of time, yet this lets not the Countries from preſenting uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls to him and his Councel, making them clear, without ſcruples, the which no queſtion but he will, as occaſions will give way, take into conſideration: This being ſo, what cauſe of complaint have you againſt him, for that which your ſelves are cauſes of? reflect then as well as proſpect, and ſo you will ſee that your errors are <hi>errant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and Law, and theſe our pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges (I conceive) are anſwered, and provided for.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Suppoſe next, that neither</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="109">109. <hi>Magna,</hi> nor Law will allow preſſing of Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, &amp;c. only beat the Drum, and ſo take all that will come, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But ſuppoſe none come, or very few, and ſo, much ſhort for number and fitneſs for the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for the whole Land being Sects, Parties, and Factions, none it may be will come, but ſuch as are for, and ſo like of the Deſigne: But theſe will not go againſt the King, nor thoſe will not go for the Lord Protector, they own not the Power, nor the cauſe, &amp;c. All which we have now ſatisfied. The Sects alſo oppoſe one another, and only ſide with themſelves, What now ſhall we do? Admit we are exigented,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:151178:42"/>
and the Magiſtrates wiſdom and faithfulneſs enjoyns him againſt all dangers and ſufferings of the People, and to all, accommodation, and his honour lies there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and Law, will not allow there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; ſo he muſt ſit ſtill, and ſee <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and Law, deſtroy his Country, by giving way to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections, and forraigne Invaſions, as wanting Souldiery to make oppoſition, Can Law or Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers anſwer this? No, no, our principles, and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions (ſure) are too hard for them all: Save the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple any way then, oh ye men of Might, though you deſtroy the Law, and &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly ſuppoſe,</hi> That</p>
            <p n="110">110. <hi>Magna,</hi> and Law, &amp;c. will not allow Tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es nor Seſments, nor to raiſe money or means any way, without a Parliament, &amp;c. yet the Governours place as afore, is to ſave us, which he cannot do, for our great Priviledges by Law, <hi>Magna,</hi> &amp;c. is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy us rather, by not allowing ſuch ſavings, though on exigents; for this ſee Sect. 113. and be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
            <p n="111">111. What need I inſtance more? this foot of <hi>Hercules</hi> hints to you what his whole body is, and ſo how to ſhape his garments for him.</p>
            <p n="112">112. The priviledges of <hi>Magna,</hi> &amp;c. I allow of and claim, as we are capable of them, but we diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim them, and muſt be allow'd to provide againſt their malgnity; if ſaving <hi>Magna Charta</hi> (through our failings) on exigencies will deſtroy us, as afore is inſtanced.</p>
            <p n="113">113. Now if the higheſt Judge who is truſted to the uttermoſt of Truſt, ſhal preſs for, or take courſe for means, beyond what Law hath provided for, and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:151178:43"/>
ſhal urge the publike occaſions for them, and addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are thereon to the Judges, to know the Law, ſure, I conceive the Judges are quit, if they comply to the higheſt Judge, as if to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and make anſwer, that the Higheſt Power is Univerſal Judge both of particulars, and for the Publike, as was <hi>Moſes;</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars to eaſe himſelf, he hath made us Judges of, yet given us the Laws for our guide, and ſo not left us to our wils, nor own judgements; and this power he may at pleaſure cal for, and place it where he pleaſe; the publike Power for judging and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, he hath reſerved to himſelf, ſo we have not to do with, but we can tel you, that if it be demanded for the Publike, then by the inſtances at <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> its Law ſufficient; for the Law is not above its Lord, the Publike or common good, and for the truth of his pretence you muſt not diſhonour him with ſuſpition, whom al the people have honoured with ſo high a Truſt, and its conceived that he wil not ſo abuſe the Truſt of the People, nor abaſe his own honour: ſo as to trecherize it to them; ſo, he hath Law on his ſide, though Law ſide not with him, or be againſt him, as its for the Lord of the Law, and as he is impowered, truſted, and made judge of al relating thereto, and as his faithfulneſs enjoyns him; ſo for the preſent either comply, or addreſs to him, as at Sect. 124.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe I have hinted that I conceived the beſt courſe to deal prevailingly and ſafely with thoſe of higheſt power and place, &amp;c. (whoever they be) is with wel and lin'd Language,<note place="margin">Penn'd.</note> and fitting addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, &amp;c. I wil here therefore for this once, indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidualize, and venture humbly to ſolicite his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:151178:43"/>
in behalf of himſelf, ſo of our ſelves, with theſe poor following Lines of mine, til abler Pens ſhal un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake it.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>To his Highneſs the Lord Protector.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>May it pleaſe your Highneſs,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>That like as God deſcended to hear his ſervants, <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Moſes,</hi> in behalf of himſelf,<note place="margin">124.</note> and his and their people, &amp;c. and as <hi>Man</hi> (viz. <hi>the</hi> Syrian <hi>and</hi> Job <hi>their ſervants, and</hi> David <hi>and</hi> Solomon <hi>the Tekoite and the two Harlots</hi>) alſo deſcended to do as much, and ſo imitated God in that kinde, ſo you will be pleaſed to imitate God, and ſuch good men, and do the like in behalf of your ſelf, and your people &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Your ſervant ſaith then, to your Highneſs, as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> to God; <hi>God forbid the juſt God ſhould be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt:</hi> and as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid, <hi>Raze me out of thy Book, rather then thy Honour, thy great Name,</hi> or this Thy People ſhould ſuffer; <hi>for what wil the Gentiles ſay, if ſo?</hi> or, what is't they will not ſay, &amp;c. to the great diſhonour of thy great Name, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>In both which ſayings they aym at the Honour of God, and good of his people: as firſt, that they would not have Gods honour any way to ſuffer, or receive the leaſt touch or tincture of any blemiſh or abaſement; but that as he is a juct God, ſo his proceedings ſhould anſwer it, leſt it reflect on him to his diſhonour: Next, they take care of their People and Brethren, and ſo preſs God thereafter, and God complies to them both, in both, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:151178:44"/>
                     <note place="margin">In point of power.</note>Now ſeeing that by God himſelf you are a God on earth, theſe ſayings Sir, relate to you alſo (as you ſo relate) in points of your own honour, ſo of your Peoples welfare, &amp;c. yet know Sir, that the ſame God ſaith alſo, that you are but a <hi>Man,</hi> and like a <hi>Man</hi> must die; and man, Gods ſervant, makes bold likewiſe to ſay as much; and without either of their ſayings, your experience <hi>(Sir)</hi> knows and ſaith it alſo.</p>
                  <p>Your ſervant doth then most humbly beſeech your Highneſs (as <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> did God afore) by all that doth or can engage man, or is neer and dear to him, and ſo prevalent with him, that for your own Honors ſake, and next, for your peoples ſake, you will hear him in behalf of both, and comply accordingly, or raze him out of your<note place="margin">Of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> Book alſo, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> That your great Name, Fame, and Renown, may not receive the leaſt tincture, blemiſh, or abaſement, but that it may appear clear, bright, fair and full to all eyes, and ſo may attract awe, admiration, and reverence, and conduce to a full heightning thereof, and that as well from Heathens and Pagans, as Chriſtians. ſo from Forraigne and ſtranger States, Princes, and People, as from your own, that ſo if the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> ſhall chance to hear thereof, and ſo give your Highneſs a viſit, ſhe may double her devoiions, and admiration of your wiſdom and goodneſs, by your wiſe, juſt and well-governing, and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyfying the People under your charge; as, by accomoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them with what good Laws, and lawful Liberties you may, and eaſing them of what preſſures and ſufferings you may alſo, and giving them fair ſatiisfaction for the reſt; and then may you Sir, like God, with much honour, &amp;c. aſcend in your ſeeming deſcention of giving accompt, which is rather wiſely to call to accompt, by
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:151178:44"/>
ſetting off your own <hi>Heroick</hi> integrity, ſo your Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Worthyneſs of minde and ſpirit, in all your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, which dare the <hi>Eagles</hi> eye, and the illuſtrious and all-ſeeing <hi>Sun</hi>'s penetrations in his height of bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: Next, in ſetting out your Adverſaries unjuſt <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taliation</hi> by their inſenſibleneſs, neglects, and ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude; yea more, as, by their rude, their bold, and uncivil cenſures, clamours, and exclamations of all ſorts; yea, further or most of all, by their Clandeſtines and Treche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of all kinds: And on theſe grounds you may Sir, as did God himſelf, appeal in a God-like poſture, and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage ſutable. What is't O my adverſaries of all ſorts, that you can require more at my hands, by way of acco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation, then I have done? What leſs by way of offence? And yet conſider with your ſelves how you have retaliated me! For what more wrong can you do me by way of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, Neglect, and Diſ-reſpect, then you have done! and yet, more you have done in your bold, rude, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civil clamours and exclamations, &amp;c. yea, the moſt you can do, in your Trecheries and Rebellions of all ſorts? What leſs can you do in point of compenſation, by way of Honour, Love, and Service, then to do nothing at all, or what's worſe then all, as the quite contrary, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Judge then your ſelves, Oh <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> of <hi>Mine</hi> and <hi>Your</hi> Ways; Is't fair that you retaliate nothing for all things, or ſome things worſe then nothing? As wilde Grapes for Tame; and Thorns and Thiſtles for Roſe-buds and Violets.</p>
                  <p>Yea, oh unſpeakable!<note place="margin">Hard u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage.</note> Have you not crown'd me with Thorns and Thiſtles, inſteed of the flowery Coronets and Chaplets, of Myrtle, Bays, and Lawrel,<note place="margin">Grief at your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude</note> acquir'd and merited for your ſakes, and ſo have drawn blood both from my head and my heart.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:151178:45"/>Thus doing, your People ſhall meet you, as did <hi>Jeph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tah</hi>'s daughter her father, with her conſorts and damſels, tryumphantly, with plaudites and acclamation of joy and prayſes, ſo with prayers for your long and happy continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance amongst them; and if your Highneſs pleaſe to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach your People, it ſhall be like the Summer Suns acceſſion on Winters retreat; and your retreat Sir from them ſhall be like his.</p>
                  <p>Can you Sir, or any Governour, receive greater Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Glory, and Renown, or ſweeter content, then by ſuch Sun-like doings as afore on your part, and then on the Peoples part ſuch joy and cheerfulneſs, with acc<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>amations to you for the ſame, acknowledging you the Father and Sun of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> &amp;c. Conſider I beſeech you Sir of what I ſay, and ſo leave your name renown'd, when you have left this tranſitory world, by immortaliZing it as afore; and whilſt you are here Sir, it will ſurely conduce to prolong your days, beſides happyfying them; for who dares or will attempt againſt ſuch a <hi>Heroe?</hi> And yet truly Sir, there is no ſecurity in<note place="margin">Too much confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</note> 
                     <hi>ſecurity;</hi> for as our Saviour ſaid, He knew what was in man, ſo would not truſt him; So we know not what's in man, and therefore muſt not truſt him, and yet we muſt, and not ſeem to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrust him though we do.</p>
                  <p>But Sir, I am afraid that I have tranſgreſt both in quantity and quality, as failing of a fitting Dialect, ſo by encroaching on your Highneſs patience in prolixing it, Here then I period: And yet who can check and take off himſelf on ſo ſpacious and uſeful a ſubject? but I muſt and will: Only I do with all humility crave pardon for my failings any way; However Sir, they are of weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and not of wickedneſs; and I conceive it will ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:151178:45"/>
your Highneſs to make the beſt of fair intentio<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s and endeavours, and to pardon the truly penitent: And now I have done, only venture to ſubſcribe my ſelf</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your HIGHNES moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Servant, S. H.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Truly if the aforeſaid courſe and way wil not avail and do, I ſee not but that the Governour and governed, Prince and people, one or both are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done; for Factions and Arms uſually attend both ſides, to the ruine of both.</p>
            <p n="125">125. But I foreſee that there are ſpirits that wil object againſt what's ſaid in behalf of Governours in points of honouring, cringing, and bowing to them, ſo for entitleing, and Petitioning to, &amp;c. and ſay, Why all this trow? We know whence Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours are; I am of as good a Houſe and Family, Name and Breed, as is he &amp;c. They are men, and no more, if ſo much; ſtrip, and we are alike, or I may paſs for him, and he for me; into the world we come alike, and ſo we ſhall go out: Who ſhal in the Charnel houſe diſtinguiſh from Kings Princes, and Peers, and other men? Nay, it may be mean men may paſs for the mighty, &amp;c. Beſides, it prides the already proud, and it inviteth them to contemn their Brethren, who by Nature are alike, and in Grace it may be much unlike, as far beyond them, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I muſt and wil yeild to Truths, as that there are inconveniencies on both ſides; Firſt, Sufferings by the govern'd, by the Governours, as afore; ſo it ſhal do wel in thoſe that ſupply the place of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, or any other, to ſay to them as <hi>Samuel</hi> to
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:151178:46"/>
               <hi>Saul,</hi> 1 Sam. 15.17. and <hi>Nathan</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> 2 Sam. 12.7, 8. the Lord hath rais'd thee to this and that, alſo thou haſt had, and now haſt, and mayſt have ſo and ſo; Why then thus? Why ſo and ſo? &amp;c. And thus <hi>memorandum</hi> them modeſtly what they are, and whence, and whither they muſt, &amp;c. and ſo cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion them againſt contempt, and injuring their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the People, and to al kinds of accomodations of them.</p>
            <p>Next, theſe inconveniences following, fal on the Governours ſide, by reaſon of the Peoples igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and want of ſelf-government, <hi>viz.</hi> ſlightings and contempts, oft to diſobedience and rebellion, to the ruine of both ſides; ſo that Governours are enforc'd to uſe force, alſo publikely to <hi>State</hi> it, and to aſſume or entertain Titles, and al kind of ſpecious pretenſes, and awful preſentments (though ſelf-ly humble, and contemners of al) only to beget awe, reverence, and reſpect; and ſo obedience, peace and quiet; and to quit the contrary &amp;c. And God in Scriptures allows of Titles; as my King, &amp;c. yea of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> my King, mine Anointed; nay, God doth <hi>hyperbolize</hi> it, and ſaith of al Powers, You are gods; and if gods, what not in point of Titles, ſo of al an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerables? As in <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> and divers others, both for State and Eſtates: As juſt and wiſe policies adviſe to for conducings ſake, and againſt al unjuſt ſeducings, abuſings, or betrayings thereby &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But none I ſay did ever Monarchize or King it as did <hi>Moſes,</hi> though never King'd, nor Titled, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted by the People, yet ſufficiently and authenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally inveſted and authoriſed, as we have proved,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:151178:46"/>
and being anſwerably aided both from Heaven and Earth againſt his rebellious oppoſers, titles or ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous taking or overtaking preſentments of any kinde, he needed not, having ſuch chaſtiſing Miracles to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend him, as made him awful, and rendred him ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like a God then a man, in point of Power; for Thunder, Lightning, Storms and Tempeſts attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him from Heaven; and from Hel or the Earth, Earthquakes, Chaſmaes, and Voragoes were at his command &amp;c. Theſe attract awe, reverence, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience ſufficiently; ſo he needed not any other <hi>at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractions,</hi> as Titles, or the Glories and Braveries of a Court; but where they are not, <hi>Conſpicuities</hi> may be of conſequence: For al Powers are not furniſhed with Thunderbolts from Heaven, as was <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo nor with Chaſmaes and Whirl-pits from Hel, as was He.</p>
            <p>Again, we bow and bend to al Inferiour Powers, with a reverend and humble reſpect, as to our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and Maſters, entitling them according to their Relations, Places, and Degrees; alſo obey and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence them: and as occaſion is of gaining any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, or to attain forgiveneſs of any offence, we beg and entreat, and bend alſo; yea and kneel it; and what's al this but in nature petitioning, the like to Governours, that yet are governed by the higheſt Governour; we ſtand bare, bow and bend, alſo pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition them, and that with humble language and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, anſwerable to their Places and Powers; as we would gain favours, yea Juſtice, and our Rights, &amp;c. or to pardon our offences &amp;c. Thus we do to Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of our Hall-companies, ſo to the Lord Mayor, the Judges, and al ſorts of Magiſtrates &amp;c. and wil
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:151178:47"/>
you do leſs to the higheſt Powers? And if it be more, yet it may be leſs, and not ſo much by way of proportion, conſidering them with the Governours afore: Object no more then, but perform your du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties by giving them their dues &amp;c. And for any ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection you can bring out of Scripture, as, you ſhal not affect Titles, nor give Titles to any man, nor call nor be call'd gracious lords; had I time, I can eaſily anſwer them by Scriptures, ſo by Reaſon, which is Scripture to the wiſe, and its in part done already, by what's done: Is not Sarah com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for obeying, and lording her husband <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham?</hi> and yet they were conſorts. <hi>Potiphars</hi> wife preſerv'd her ſelf in al things concerning <hi>Joſeph,</hi> til her lord came home. What's due then from the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote in Degree and Relation, if <hi>ſuch</hi> Relates muſt ſo retaliate? Chriſt the contemner of Titles and vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glories in himſelf, as not of this world, yet ſaid, <hi>You ſay well, I am your Lord and maſter, &amp;c.</hi> But I cannot further enlarge, and to the wiſe I need not, and to the wilful I wil not; ſo I do for this time period this point.</p>
            <p n="126">126. And now I wil make bold with a few words to all ſtranger Princes and States, Powers and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates of all kinds, neer or remote, in behalf of their people, ſo of themſelves and us.</p>
            <p>To you then, oh you Soveraigne Powers &amp;c. I addreſs my ſelf in theſe following lines.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <p>BE pleaſed to take notice, that much of what's ſaid to his Highneſs our own Governour, relates to, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns you alſo; what ſo doth, you may more ſelf-ly apply;
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:151178:47"/>
what not, paſs by. However, I hope that you will find, that I have done you (not only) all the Right I can, but all that can be done you, Juſtice: So your Honours, and great Names and Renowns, enjoyn Retaliation anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in points of Protection, and happyfying the People under you, that have denuded themſelves of all their Powers, and inveſted you therewith, and by ſo great a Be-truſt have put themſelves wholly into your hands and powers, reſting only on your Honours Nobleneſs and Faithfulneſs towards them; which to forfeit or fail of, I want expreſſions to ſay what it is: Let (if not a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian yet) a Pagan principle prevail with you, for though delivered by a Chriſtian, as by Chriſt himſelf, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to all Chriſtians; yet its a Natural, a Rational, a Moral, and ſo a Gentile Principle likewiſe, and belongs to man as a man; ſo that if Religion will avail with you, ſo; if not, yet Reaſon and Gentiliſme muſt, ſo you muſt of neceſſity, <hi>Do as you would be done to,</hi> and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taliate rightly, as afore: Take heed, Oh all you Powers, that you Atheiſme not the people by your Actions, which are ſeen into; which if you do, I know, and you may know what attends you. Teach them not, nor juſtifie them not, by your doings; You puniſh (and that juſtly) petty failings reſpectively, as Murthers, Thefts, Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries, and all perfideous dealings, &amp;c. and render ſuch baſe, and vile people: What then are your ſelves if you do the<note n="*" place="margin">With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out juſt neceſſity.</note> like? that is, Take from, or oppreſs without<note n="*" place="margin">Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like or private.</note> juſt cauſe? or bereave of Life, Limb, or Liberty: is't not murther, theft and injuſtice; and what are ſuch by your own condemnings, and executing ſuch? Is't not alſo an abaſing your ſelves in your Honours and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowns &amp;c. by ſuch diſhonourable courſes? as render you infinitely below your ſelves? Doth it not intimate
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:151178:48"/>
Atheiſme and Hypocriſie, to the ruining of Religion, and ſo your own, and all kinde of Regiments, if ſeen into by the People? For pious policies and Pretences will not alwaies hold and ſerve, if ſuch great depravings and prevarications ſecond &amp;c. Be like the Syrian <hi>(great Sirs)</hi> adviſed by your Servant, and ſee you waſh in <hi>Jor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan,</hi> and not in <hi>Damaſcus</hi> waters or rivers: Let it be your delights then, to delight and refreſh the poor ſouls that have reſign'd up into your hands; all that is, or can be neer or dear to man; as their Eſtates, their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, &amp; their Lives; for all are in your Power; yea their very Souls and Conſciences are in a manner at your command; for that extremity of ſufferings and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments may vanquiſh the moſt valiant, and cauſe them rather to venture on God then man.</p>
                  <p>How can you hear, ſee, or know of the cries, lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, languiſhings and ſufferings of the oppreſs'd poor creatures, and paſs it by? Where is Senſe, Nature, and Humanity? How doth this anſwer to Manhood, ſo to your places profeſſions, and engagements? See then that you hearken not to <hi>Rehoboams</hi> young Heads or Counſellors, but to the wiſe, the ſage, the grave &amp;c. And remember what <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>That Juſtice eſtabliſheth Thrones, and that Oppreſſions make a wiſe man mad;</hi> its eaſie to infer then what the contrary doth, ſo what in time to expect. But I have done with this point, only conclude with <hi>Lex talionis; Do, as you would be done to:</hi> Elſe how can, or why ſhould you expect, but as you perform?</p>
                  <p n="127">
                     <hi>127.</hi> And yet, Oh you Princes, Powers, and States &amp;c. though I have done, as afore; yet I have not done, ſo must begin again on another ſcore or account, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Be pleaſed then (great Sirs) to extend your Scepters,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:151178:48"/>
and ſo allow of my addreſment once more. I hope then that by this time, Oh ye Princes, ye are fully ſatisfied about the right of our Worthy Governour to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. and that your Peer Prince, as call'd, hath no right thereto, as having forfeited it; beſides all our other Arguments againſt him, theſe ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing clear without the leaſt ſcruple; ſure you cannot act or proceed againſt the light of Religion, Reaſon, Nature, Juſtice, and Rights, and ſo againſt God: I hope you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not nor will not ſo abaſe your Honours, Fames, and great Names, &amp;c. Convince us, Oh you Princes, Convince us, for thats Prince-like; and then if we comply not, you have ſome colour to compel; otherwiſe <hi>Club-law is Peaſant,</hi> and not <hi>Prince-like.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We hope then, yea we build on your Honours Renowns and Noble Natures, that you will not under pretence of a Princes Right, unjuſtly invade or molest us, ſeeing we have diſproved it; which if you do, we hope our God will go along with us, as he hath done hitherto; and why ſhould you (Oh ye Princes) maligne or oppoſe a juſt Prince our Governour, whom you find by our Arguments not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worthy of it, but to have as great a Right to it: Sure, you are Chriſtians, and if not, yet you are men, you are Gentiles then &amp;c. We ſhall deſire no more of you then of Gentiles, who by Nature knew and did the Law &amp;c. which do you likewiſe, and then we have done, and ſo have you, if ſo you will have done; for I am ſure we may be ſecure; cauſe you may not by the Pagans or Gentiles Laws do otherwiſe then whats right, and ſo will not come nor ſend hither unjuſtly, or hoſtilely invade us; which if you do, we hope the God, the Lord of Hosts will be for us, as afore &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Be adviſed and take heed (Oh Princes) what you do;
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:151178:49"/>
and know that the name of War &amp;c. though your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences ſeem never ſo juſt, will not quit your killing from murthers, nor your takings from, and ſpoylings, from Thefts; Here <hi>Lex talionis</hi> calls on you again, for your Renowns ſake ſee you anſwer it: Had you juſt cauſe to invade and hoſtile it againſt us, and we would not give you ſatisfaction, I would not ſpeak; but as the caſe ſtands I may not be ſilent. Had we juſt cauſe to invade you, it concerns you to ſay as much to us by way of ſatisfaction: but if we have no cauſe, its better for us to ſit ſtill, then riſe to fall; its the like for you. And if any of your ſelves or your People ſhould plot to aſſaſſinate our Worthy Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour at all. How then our Arguments conſidered? Let thoſe who have a hand therein know, that what they do, they teach to do; they juſtifie and warrant to be done to them by <hi>Lex talionis,</hi> ſo endanger your ſelves thereby, but Wiſdom, Policy, Equity, Juſtice, God, Nature, Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Reaſon, ſo your Honours and Renowns, forbid to do, or teach ſuch doings; and we conceive that there is not any of you will rebel againſt them all; ſo our hopes are (Oh you men of Might, Power, Place, and Renown) that you will not ſo abaſe your Honours and great Names, and ſo not act any thing that ſhall blemiſh, or ſtain the beauty, glory, and luſter of your Renowns, but do as you would be done to, or expect to be done ſo to, by right of Retaliation. But on preſumption of your Noble Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Honours, and Renowns, I will not preſume any further to offend by prolix or tedious enlargements, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept to ſubſcribe my ſelf</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Majeſties &amp;c. moſt humble Servant <hi>S. H.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p n="127">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:151178:49"/>127. But leſt our other worthy Commanders; Officers, and Souldiery of all ſorts, ſhould conceive themſelves wrong'd, ſlighted, or neglected, for that all the brave atchievements are only attributed to his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> they having perform'd ſo worthily as they did. I do anſwer them, that I do take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of their worthy and brave performances, and do here acknowledge them; only this place allows not individual acknowledgement by <hi>Encomiums</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable, which ſome able pen ſhould do wel to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake: I hope alſo that they are not to ſeek, that in great atchievements, the honour and praiſe is uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally contracted, by attributing it to the General, or prime Commander and Manager of al, as being too hard and tedious to delineate each individual perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance. And there is ſome reaſon for the aforeſaids, cauſe if things miſcarry under the ſaid General, in his management of them, though he fail neither in wiſdom, care, faithfulneſs, nor fortitude: but only ſome of his ſubordinate Commanders, Officers, or Souldiery do; yet the diſhonour is attributed to him only, and they go free: Retaliation then wil do him this Juſtice and Right, as ſo to compenſate him rightly for ſuch wrong &amp;c. Thus the <hi>Sweden</hi> King, ſo the great <hi>Alexander,</hi> likewiſe <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Spinola,</hi> with <hi>Scanderbeg,</hi> and many others, did contract and magazine al the Honour &amp;c. in their own names, which (no queſtion) ſome of their Commanders, Officers, and Souldiery had a great ſhare in, as help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to purchaſe it by their brave performances; and their Antagoniſts, <hi>Tilly, Darius, Pompey</hi> &amp;c. loſt the Honour; yet it may be not by any failing in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but by the failings of ſome of their ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:151178:50"/>
Commanders, Officers, and Souldiery &amp;c. or by ſome accident: And thus I hope the generous Souldiery of al ſorts wil be ſatisfied, and my Readers alſo reſt reſolv'd &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="128">128. I have now done, only I wil conclude <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radoxically,</hi> as venture to entertain a hope beyond or againſt hope; as that the world is grown ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious that none will take exceptions at what I have writ, no, though I accidentally croſs them in their private ends, as they croſs themſelves and theirs, in croſſing the Publike, which in concluſion wil one way or other tend to individual ſufferings and croſſes; al which I labour to prevent, by endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to prevent diviſions and factions; ſo the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging and forraging ſword, likewiſe fire and famine, with al kinds of devaſtations and miſeries attending war; that ſo they may live in peace and ſafety, and enjoy one another, ſo what they have, with ſweet and ſerene quiet and content &amp;c. and if for this they wil hate me, I am out of al hopes ever to gain their love, though I merit it; for I cannot, nor can any expreſs love, care, faithfulneſs, or affection, beyond the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaids: And now I have done, being come to <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les pillars,</hi> or <hi>Ne plus ultra,</hi> my</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:151178:50"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>MY earneſt deſire to make ſure worke before I end, hath begot theſe following Lines.</p>
            <p>Its conſiderable, that the expreſſion Parliament as ours of late are condition'd) is accepted too en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely, as if a fair and wel-body'd Unite, compos'd and made up of many Individuals, or Unites, in that one Body, as if alſo united in their hearts, judgments, ends, and aims for the Publike good, as are their preſentments and pretences, and ſo were diſclaimers of al ſelf-ends, as they claſh therewith; but we find it otherwiſe: For firſt, inſtead of the honourable name of a Parliament, which (if right) is their due, they are (if diſſected) in the <hi>general,</hi> a compoſition of Sects, Factions, and Parties divided (in that ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, entire, and united fair (Unite, or Body) &amp;c. who have their ſelf-ends, in oppoſition one of another, and al of them in neglect and oppoſition of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, as it affronts their particulars: In ſhort, its like a divided Kingdom, and ſo its rather a Kings-<note n="*" place="margin">Ruine of any Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</note> Doom, then a Kingdom, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thus conſidered, To whom ſhould his Highneſs and the Souldiery have reſign'd their Powers? Not to a Parliament ſure in the right ſenſe, but to a divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Kingdom, as to ſeveral parties and factions, to enable them to ruine one another and al of them the Publick, whereas the General and Souldiery preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them from ſo doing or being ſo done to; for they would have fallen foul, or out amongſt themſelves, and contented for the Power, only to over-power the reſt, and the Presbyterie were the moſt likely to
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:151178:51"/>
carry it, as to appearance the ſtrongeſt party, as the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> ſtory makes good, whoſe Principles are to <hi>Prince</hi> themſelves, and precipitate al ſorts, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the notion of Sects &amp;c. al which his Highneſs and the Army foreſeeing, how can it in Reaſon or Religion be expected that they ſhould ſo tamely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver up their Power to ſeveral parties, as fore, al adverſe to one another, ſo to his Highneſs and his party alſo, and that under the notion and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as if to a Parliament rightly conſtituted.</p>
            <p>Each party or faction alſo deſires and endeavours for the Power, only to overpower the reſt, &amp;c. Do they not then juſtifie his Highneſs and his Party, who have it, to hold it, whoſe Principles are only publike, and ſelf preſervation; and his precepts and practiſe hitherto make it good? Do they not then condemn themſelves, for condemning him? I appeal.</p>
            <p>Certainly, if wiſe each party were, they would be glad he hath and holds the Power; for ſhould he reſigne it amongſt them, it would enforce them to implore his re-acceptance thereof, to prevent the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation of their Lives and Beings, by deſtructive conteſts about it.</p>
            <p>Parliaments (if right) I honour as much as any, and I know that there was in each of them many wiſe and good men, worthy of honour, which I may not here individualize; But what's this to the multitude, amongſt whom the honour and reputation of ſuch are loſt, as was Chriſt in the croud? And as are the reputations of many wiſe and good men, who ſuffer in and under the general notion of the giddy headed multitude.</p>
            <p>I ſay as much by al notion'd Sects, Parties, Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:151178:51"/>
and Churches, or however call'd, that there are many wiſe and good men amongſt al ſorts of them, but they are in points of reputation and diſtinction loſt alſo (as afore) in the multitude, and ſo ſuffer as much as the moſt inſufferable amongſt them.</p>
            <p>But 'cauſe al ſorts are ſo choiſe of their Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, let them chuſe of the choyceſt, as of thoſe ſo prais'd in Scripture, as afore: Let's know your minds then, whether you wil have <hi>Moſes</hi> or <hi>Joſhua,</hi> or <hi>Saul, David,</hi> or <hi>Solomon;</hi> whereof if you chuſe, you know what to truſt to by their ſtories; Be wel advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed then before any of them be ſent for, or elſe give God Almighty time and directions to creat you one.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But the Lord</hi> Fairfax <hi>deliver'd up his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and Power without all this ado, and no ſuch Iſſues enſu'd thereon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What are Examples to Arguments? Are accidental Iſſues alſo grounds for wiſe men? And yet the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> might ſee himſelf, ſo his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and his Party in ſafety, for that he might fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee that the Power remain'd in the hands of his own Party, as with his Souldiery, &amp;c. who ſure would not ſuffer their General to ſuffer, as would not <hi>Sauls</hi> ſervants ſee <hi>Jonathan</hi> ſuffer; an example ſomwhat ſuiting with this: And this was no diſobedience, 'cauſe ſuch an obedience was not due.</p>
            <p>Again, the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> might foreſee alſo that his Highneſs was to ſupply his place, whoſe Wiſdom, Fortitude, and Faithfulneſs, he might from experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence be confident would ſecure him, as the Souldiery did <hi>Jonathan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But his Highneſs was impowered only to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, and not to rule and govern.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:151178:52"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This <hi>Hydra</hi> multiplies in heads under vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Viſors, for expreſſions are altered, but the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection is anſwer'd afore under other Notions and Rendrings: But we wil lop off this head alſo, and ſo I hope ſend the <hi>Hyleding</hi> packing. We ſay then, that the People impower'd the Parliament to rule only, and not to over-rule, but whether they kept to this rule or no, I appeal. So if it be the Parliament that thus object, we anſwer them by themſelves, as afore. Again, we ſay, that it's not a right Parliament, but ſo many divided parties that object, and ſo its beſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd by not anſwering. If any one party, or indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual perſon object, we ſay that parties or perſons are no concluding Judges &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But we have juſtifi'd the Power where it is, by the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> ſtory, <hi>pag.</hi> 22. ſo by <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtory, <hi>page</hi> 54. <hi>Sect.</hi> 97. ſo his Highneſs own ſtory, <hi>Sect.</hi> 43. to 53. beſides divers other places, and laſtly, as appears in our <hi>Army Armed, p.</hi> 9. Again, let any one ſhew me who it is hath right at al, or ſo much as hath his Highneſs, al things conſidered, ſeeing the King of Scot's race is raz'd out by the whole Nation, and ſo by every Individual, as by their Parliament.</p>
            <p>But it's time I give over, having (I'm afraid) wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed my Readers as wel as my ſelf, as having ſurpriz'd them of their better pleaſures, delights, and refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſo of their ſweet retired Retreats; but I'le endeavour to make them amends by an ingenious acknowledgement, ſo alſo (if I can) by accomoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them with a more pleaſing piece or ſubject, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And yet I had need begin again, and write as much in defence of what I have writ, as it ſelf is: For, <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorn Hope-like,</hi> I have expos'd my ſelf almoſt to the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:151178:52"/>
enmity of al the world, except I have won upon any ingenious and judicious ſpirits, which are very rare to be found: I am then in thine hands Courteous Reader, Uſe me humanely and civilly, I pray thee, and I deſire no more; and leſs thou canſt not in ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice do me: If then thou findſt me failing, or ſhort in any thing, or ſeeſt more, or beyond me, pride it not, nor contemn me, but know thou art advanc'd on our ſhoulders, ſo on others, and ſo haſt thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect ample, clear, and fair about thee; and thy ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial <hi>Opticks</hi> and Proſpectives alſo, to amplifie thy ſight, and diſpel <hi>Opacity.</hi> But wert thou hous'd in ſome dark or Proſpectleſs ground room, and ſo muſt fetch in al by thy own natural Proſpectives only, as by thy graſping and comprehenſive underſtanding, as do Silk-worms and Spiders their curioſities, out of their own Bowels, then wouldſt thou like <hi>Job</hi> in another caſe, ſee thy error, and cry out with him, Once, yea twice have I ſpoken, &amp;c. but for future wil be wiſer, and ſo compreſs or remiſs it. But charm the Charmer never ſo ably, yet the deaf Adder wil not hear, &amp;c. ſo if our Reader wil not comply to apparent Reaſon,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.32.</note> then am I forc'd to conclude a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch, that I have had to do al this while with <hi>Epheſians,</hi> &amp;c. Note the next, &amp;c. That</p>
            <p>The Epiſtle to Forraign Princes and States was writ as hints and cautions to them, upon hearing of the unheard of, barbarous and helliſh maſſacring of the Proteſtant Waldenſes, which through them ſtrikes at all Proteſtants. Oh murtherous Religion, <hi>alias,</hi> a cunning Regiment under the name thereof! Be wiſe, oh ye Govetnours of all ſorts.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:151178:53"/>But if after all this pains taken to ſatisfie all ſorts, for their own good, as their peace and ſafety, ſo for the Publick Good, peace and ſafety alſo, they yet will not inquire after ſuch <hi>Books,</hi> as will ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure them; or if they meet with them, yet not read them thorough, but onely here and there, and ſo may chance to meet with ſomething, that rather <hi>offends,</hi> then <hi>ſatisfies</hi> them, which is provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for preſently after, or in ſome other place; or if they do read it through, and then caſt it by, as if never of uſe more, and ſo after a while forget all, or many uſefull concernments; ſo that if their own <hi>hearts, ſuggeſt, except,</hi> or <hi>object</hi> this, or that, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or if they ſhall hear others do ſo, they are not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for either, and <hi>repair</hi> to the <hi>Book</hi> for <hi>ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> they will not; what ſhall we ſay then to ſuch, but as afore, that wee have had to doe with <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why alſo doe not Friends, that have read ſuch Books, mind their friends and acquaintance of them, that ſo <hi>Univerſal</hi> ſatisfaction may be, and the <hi>bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit</hi> of <hi>Peace, Quiet,</hi> and <hi>Safety</hi> anſwerable thereto.</p>
            <p>Courteous Reader, <hi>The thing that I fear'd is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len upon me, for the</hi> Errata <hi>hath made work for thy goodneſſe and humanity, it might have been thy own caſe as its mine,</hi> do as thou wouldſt be done to, <hi>and ſo here is no</hi> Errata, <hi>though there be almoſt nothing elſe; however if thou finds them not, I will not.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eccleſ. 9.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p> There was a poor man ſav'd a City, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eſt. 6.1, 2:</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p> Ahaſhuerus read the Cronicles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <closer>
               <salute>VALE.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
